Hi folks, I'm Shashank. I work with Ditto Insurance. We are an insurance advisory platform
where we deal with health and term insurance plans. Now, if you are out here looking for
quality advice, then we recommend you to book a free of course consultation with our advisors
with the link in the description. With the introduction out of the way, folks, let me
now introduce our guest today, Sushant. He is the Senior Program Manager here at Ditto.
And today we are going to talk about Aditya Birla's Sun Life Insurance. Sushant, welcome
to the podcast. Thanks for having me. So Sushant, let's start with the introduction and the
basic metrics, how they're operating. So take us through the details. So they actually do
have quite an interesting story. Aditya Birla Sun Life was established in the year 2000.
And it's actually a joint venture between Aditya Birla Capital and Sun Life Insurance
Inc. from Canada. So yeah, and I think over the last 20-25 years, they've really established
themselves by offering a very diversified portfolio of plans, ranging from term insurance
to ULIPs to endowments, even child plans and retirement plans as well. So I think they've
really tried to cater to pretty much all the sort of sectors of the audience.
Alright, alright. And how are they operationally? I think if I were to talk about their metrics,
first if we look at claim settlement ratio, for example, quite good. In the recent years,
their average has been just over 98%, which is well above the industry average and a really
good number. If I were to talk about amount settlement ratio, pretty solid in that front
too, about 94% change, which is pretty good. Coming to the complaints volume, very reasonable.
For every 10,000 claims, they've had just five complaints. Once again, that's well below
the industry average. And in terms of annual business, they've been growing steadily year
on year. So we're looking at about 6,500 crores of annual business per year.
Okay, pretty solid metrics over there. Now let's talk about their offerings in terms of term plans.
So they have about three term plans. If I were to pick their flagship one, which is called DigiShield.
Under that is about 10 variants or options that you can play around with. So one would be a return
of premium variant, where you get your money back at the end of the plan. One would be a whole life
cover, where you're allowed to be insured for the entirety of your life, meaning until 99 or 100
years of age. If I were to talk about the age of entry for this plan, it's about 18 to 65.
For some insured, you're allowed to buy a minimum of 30 lakhs and there's no upper limit,
which is quite interesting. Most companies set a cap that you can't buy more than 10, 20, 30 crores.
Here there is no cap, of course, subject to your eligibility and underwriting.
In terms of riders and optional benefits that they offer, there are some interesting features
there too. They have an accidental death and disability benefit, wherein for an accidental
death you're paid a higher sum in short. For an accident disability, you're paid a percentage of
the rider based on the disability that happens and this is all clearly listed out. They have a
critical illness variant, even though they have two options. So one is a critical illness accelerated
variant covering about 42 illnesses and then there's a normal critical illness variant covering just
four critical illnesses. So I feel there maybe they probably are lacking a little bit, whereas
other brands offer the 20, 30, 40 illnesses. So that's probably one place where I would say
they're slightly lacking. They also offer another free benefit called the life stage benefit,
where you're allowed to increase your sum insured up to 100% in the future based on certain life
stages like marriage and having kids. This plan also comes with an inbuilt terminal illness benefit.
In case someone's terminally ill, they can claim an accelerated amount of their term insurance.
Lastly, they have some unique features such as a surgical care rider, meaning in case you require
a surgery of some sorts, diagnosed and approved by a medical professional, they will pay up a
certain amount to financially support you. And they also have a hospice care benefit,
which very few insurance companies offer, which is more of a health insurance benefit if you ask me.
But how this feature works is once you're admitted to the hospital, if you're there for more than two
or three days, they give you a certain daily cash allowance. Daily cash is what we call it in health
insurance terms, but in term insurance they call it the hospice care benefit. So you're given a daily
allowance every day to kind of help you with miscellaneous expenses. But yeah, I think that
more or less summarizes the DigiShield plan. DigiShield is a really, really comprehensive
plan. Now, I've also gone through the brochure and they also have something called as an income
suraccia plan. Some more details on that? This actually is a very interesting take on term
insurance. They've really approached it from a different angle altogether. So even under this,
there are two variants. One is called the fixed income plan, wherein they focus on giving your
nominees the death benefit in the form of monthly income. So how they've done it is that you get to
choose what amount you want your nominees to receive. For example, you say that I want them
to receive one lakh rupees per month in case something were to happen to me. They offer this
for a fixed tenure of 10 years or the remaining of the policy tenure, whichever is higher.
So if I were to give you an example, let's say I buy a term insurance for 30 years and the person
or the insured member passes away in the 15th year. Now his family will receive one lakh per month for
the next 15 years because that was the remaining of the policy tenure. This is one example. So the
other one is the increasing income protection variant that they have. Here how it works is
whatever income you've decided that your family should receive, that amount will keep increasing
by 5% year on year from the date you've bought the plan. The tenure here remains the same. The
payout tenure is 120 months or 10 years basically. So meaning if someone has bought a plan and five
years later he were to pass away. Now initially when he bought the plan, he opted for one lakh
rupees as monthly income. But in those five years this has been compounding. So now five years later
when something happens, his family is eligible to receive 1.21 lakhs or so approximately per month.
And this will still keep increasing as it's paid out until it reaches an upper cap of about 1.5
lakh rupees. So basically 1.5 times of the income you asked for. Should you have asked for 2 lakhs,
it will grow until it reaches 3 lakhs. 1.5x essentially. Understood. Quite interesting
variance. I think something unheard of altogether in term insurance. True. But if you were to ask me
and we even consulted with a few financial experts, they're also of the opinion that look maybe this
variant isn't the most helpful or beneficial. And like I said I'm of the same opinion as well.
I believe with term insurance or life insurance should have a lump sum payout to the nominees or
family members. Exactly. Reason being this gives them the flexibility to do what they want with the
money. You're not leaving it with someone and saying that look I'm happy with the lack of month.
I'd rather the family gets the one or two crores and one if they have any major debts they can
clear them off. They have some big expenses coming up it might support them. Or two at least they can
open something as simple as an FD and kind of generate six seven percent interest every year.
Right. So you have a steady flow of income while you also have that corpus line as a security in
the bank. Makes sense. So from a financial standpoint I would still always go for a lump sum option.
But I think just how interesting and unique these were I think definitely worth discussing.
Definitely definitely worth mentioning. Now we've covered both these plans. Let's quickly
go into the third plan. So the last variant is called the salaried term plan. As the name suggests
is something that's specifically for salaried individuals only. It comes with some unique
benefits but in a way it's also similar to their DG Shield plan. Okay. Let's say in terms of the
age of entry firstly right 18 to 65 is the maximum age of entry. The duration they were allowed a
maximum tenure of up to 70 years. That's the capping they've set. In terms of the cover amount
25 lakhs is the bare minimum you can choose. And there's no upper limit of course subject to
underwriting and your financial eligibility. It comes with the free rider of terminalist benefits
so that's an added advantage as well. Pricing I think is where they really stand out right.
They've they've really designed this in such a way that they offer some additional discounts
for salaried individuals and also on the basis of gender. Okay. Like we've seen before in term
insurance for females the prices can be lower right considering a higher mortality rate and
longer life expectancy. So these are some of the broad sort of overview if I had to cover them.
In terms of specific pricing though if I had to talk about some numbers for a 25 year old male
buying a one crore term plan the salaried term plan would cost about 9500 or so per year.
Their DG Shield plan would cost about 11000 change and the income plan that we spoke about
that would be somewhere around 25-26000 per year for an income of about 50 000 rupees per month
should something happen. So this is what you can see from the pricing that yes this one is priced
quite competitively right even compared to the DG Shield plan. Correct. And in case if I were
to increase the age of the individual to 35 from 25 what was 9000 change would now become 14000.
The DG Shield which used to be 11 would be about 15-16 and the income plan which is about 25 000
earlier is now looking at about 28-29 000. So more or less a proportion increase nothing significant
sort of stands out here. Alright so now in terms of the recommendations that we have at the you
know max life HDFC life so how are the premiums priced based on that. So once again let me give
it you with an example of the same profile a 25 year old one crore plan till 65. The DG Shield
plan was about 11500-1600. The salary term plan was about 9500 or so. This is the benchmark we've
set for Atia Birla. Coming to max life they're reasonably priced quite close somewhere about
10100 a year. ICIC is a bit higher at about 10900 and HDFC is even more expensive than the DG Shield
plan they're about 11900. So I think yeah this is what it would compare like you can see they're
quite competitive nothing really stands out or no added advantage either. So they're offering
similar prices but they're also you know competing with some of the largest players out there in the
industry. Alright so finally what's the final word on Atia Birla's and life insurance. So I
think based on our analysis they really do stand out as a solid player right like we just looked
at in terms of pricing as well they're able to compete with some of the large players out there.
In terms of features they're quite comprehensive they offer the accident plans, their waiver of
premium coverage, critical illness all the benefits right that are generally available out there.
Coming to the operational metrics like we saw complaint volume as well was quite low in fact
lower than even some of these brands at about five complaints every 10 000. So honestly from
that front no complaints or no issues as such. The only thing I would say is that yes there is
smaller player when compared to the top three or top five out there. So that's something that's
up to user right whether he wishes to take that risk or would he want more peace of mind going
with one of the larger established players out there. Understood. But other than that nothing
against them they really are a good option available. That's great that's a that's a good
insight Sushant and thank you so much for going into detail of Atia Birla's and life insurance.
Now folks if you enjoyed the video don't forget to drop a like and subscribe if you haven't already
and if you have any doubts please put them in the comments below and we will see you in the next one.
Until then happy insurance hunting.