Welcome to Ditto Insurance. My name is Kavya and today we will be talking about Carejoy,
which is one of the most famous maternity plans out there.
First, we will look at who should consider this policy.
This plan is well suited for newly married couples who might need maternity,
people who need newborn coverage and people who need security against birth defects.
So, how good is Care compared to other players in the market?
First, let's look at the 3-year claim settlement ratio.
Now CARE is at 91% which compared to other players in the market is pretty decent.
Next, we have the 3 year average incurred claim ratio.
For CARE, it stands at 58% which is pretty good considering that we look at 55% to 75% as a good score.
Next up is network hospitals and centres.
So CARE has a network hospitals of 9400 which is pretty decent given other contemporaries are also in the same range.
Lastly, we have 3 year average volume of complaints.
Now this is where Care gets a little troubled.
Because in 10,000 claims, Care gets at least 31 complaints which is comparatively a higher
number if you look at HDFC.
Next we will look at variants and other key differences.
So Carejoy has two variants, Joy Today and Joy Tomorrow.
In terms of features, the maternity coverage for a 3 lakh Joy Today and 3 lakh Joy Tomorrow
is the same i.e. 35000 and for a 5 lakh variant it is 50000 in both the cases. Even the newborn
cover is same for both the variants i.e. for a 3 lakh variant it is 30k whereas a 5 lakh
variant has 50k cover. Now we are gonna talk about the differences. Maternity waiting periods
for joy today is 9 months whereas joy tomorrow is 24 months i.e. you have to wait for these
many months before you make a maternity related claim. And lastly the newborn defect cover for
which Joy today has no cover but Joy tomorrow has a cover of 50k. Next up is eligibility criteria.
Now the policy document says that 18 to 65 years ke bishme koi bhi ye plan le sakta hai but when
you go on their website to buy the plan the limit is up to 45 years and for a child it is from day
to 24 years of age Coming to the PED restrictions only benign conditions like high BP hypothyroid hernia only these are accepted The features we are gonna talk about right now are already covered in detail in this
video.
So to learn more you can tap that video and check them out.
Oh if you are new here, here's a little about Ditto.
We are an insurance advisory platform built by FinShots, India's favourite new age newsletter.
We provide honest or spam-free insurance advice about health and term insurance.
First of all, we will never push you to buy.
You can take as much time as you want.
And if you do choose to buy from us,
we will guide you through the entire journey as well as the claim settlement process.
This way, you can sit back, take your time to weigh your options and buy when you want to buy.
We are available on calls as well as WhatsApp.
So, talk to us at the link in description.
Let's look at the basic policy features.
Room rent restriction.
Now this policy has a room rent restriction of single private AC room which is pretty decent but in general we recommend a plan which does not have a room rent restriction at all.
Co-payment.
So if you enter the plan after 61 years you might have to take a 20% co-pay clause but like we said there is a mismatch between what the policy document says and what you can buy.
So check that out.
check that out. Coming to disease-wise sub-limits, thankfully there are none. And it covers 30 days
of pre-hospitalization expenses and 60 days of post-hospitalization expenses. Even the day care
treatments are covered up to the sum assured. However, domiciliary expenses, IUs treatments
and free annual health checkup are not covered. In fact, this plan does not even have a restoration
benefit. What is restoration benefit? For example, you have a plan of 10 lakhs and you use 2 lakhs
to make a claim. Now, some plans might give you a restoration of 2 lakhs back into your cover.
So again, you have a 10 lakh rupee cover for that year. This whole thing is called restoration
benefit. However, Care Health Insurance mentions on their website that there's a restoration benefit
but the plan does not really offer one.
Waiting Periods
This plan has an initial waiting period of 30 days
which is standard.
The PED waiting period is 4 years which is slightly high comparatively This plan also has a 2 year waiting period for specific illnesses and as we discussed there is a nine waiting period for care joy today
for on maternity and same 24 months for care joy tomorrow. Here is a complete list of their
specific illnesses under the plan. So for these issues you will have to wait for two years before
you make a claim. Now let's get into the standout features. Maternity coverage. This plan will give
you pre and postnatal expenses under this cover. So if you have a 3 lakh cover, you will get 35,000
of maternity coverage and if you have a 5 lakh cover, then it is 50k. But as we mentioned,
please keep in mind the waiting periods. Carejoy also provides coverage for your newborn up to 90
days so if you have a cover of 3 lakh the newborn cover would be 30,000 and if it is
5 lakh then it is 50,000. Additionally Carejoy Tomorrow offers 50k for any birth defects
your newborn might have. Let's come to the add-ons. Although this add-on is not live
yet we will be talking about no claim bonanza where you get 100% of your sum assured as
bonus if you do not make a claim for 3 years.
So how much does this plan cost?
For this we have drawn a comparison between Carejoy today and Nivabopa Aspire Platinum
Plus.
So for an adult of 30 years of age the premiums would be around 74000 in Carejoy however in
Nivabopa the premiums would be 30000.
For 2 adults of 30 years of age Carejoy today would give a plan at 82000 but Nivabopa Aspire
platinum plus would be at 42,000 which is much cheaper. Now if we look at a
family floater for two adults and one child Carejoy today would cost you around
86,000 whereas Nivabopa would cost you around 54,000 so as you can see the
features of both these plans are pretty comparable but Carejoy today is very expensive.
Similarly we have compared Carejoy tomorrow with Nivabopa Aspire
Diamond Plus and Nivabupa Health Premia Silver. As you can see the premiums for this is also
very high Okay apart from the premiums are there any issues with this plan Yes limited sum assured So as we discussed this plan offers a cover of 3 lakh or 5 lakh which might not be enough given how the medical costs are increasing
So it might be inadequate for you.
Limited Features
Carejoy has a lot of limits like room rent restrictions, co-pay clause etc which is not ideal.
Basic features are there, we get it but there are lot of good features which other plans might offer at a cheaper rate.
Pricey Premiums
For the features that Carejoy is offering, there are other plans in the market that can
give you these features at much less premiums.
Room rent restrictions.
As we said, we recommend plans having no room rent restrictions as such and this plan has
one.
So if you exceed this restriction, you will have to pay a very large share of your medical
bill which is not ideal, anyway you are paying high premiums.
One another thing, Carejoy requires you to make a 3 year payment which means 3 years
premiums ek saath. Already premiums itte high hai, wo bhi 3 saal ke would be very heavy on your pocket.
So what does Ditto recommend? See the premiums are very high. So even if you took like a normal
health plan and saved all that money, aapka maternity coverage mein utna hi kharcha hota.
So it doesn't make a lot of sense to pay so high premiums for something which you would be able to
afford without one as well. So are there any better alternatives? Maybe. One, your corporate plan
might offer you maternity cover.
So if you opt one there, you don't need to get a separate coverage.
Two, Nivabopa itself has a few plans which have better features,
better coverage and affordable premiums.
For example, plans like Nivabopa Health Premia and Aspire
might offer you better features at affordable premiums.
However, with Nivabopa, our experience has not been ideal.
For a case like a small dengue, we had to go through a lot of back and forth,
which is not ideal when you are making a claim.
You are already very busy with your own things.
So ideally, we would recommend an insurer
where there is less back and forth like this.
So finally, maternity cover lena aisa koi bahut necessary nahi hai.
You can go for a simple health insurance also.
But what you want to take is ultimately your call.
So if you want to understand more about it
or find the right health insurance plan for you,
talk to us at Ditto Insurance.
The link is in the description.
Like, share and subscribe. Happy Insurance Hunting!