You see 1 crore health insurance under 20,000 rupees and think jackpot!
But here's what most people miss, not all 1 crore policies are made equal.
So today we're breaking down one of the most talked about budget plans in the market,
Care Supreme by Care Health Insurance.
Hello folks, I'm Shashank from Ritter Insurance and in this video,
I'll walk you through everything you need to know about Care Supreme,
the eligibility features, waiting periods, bonus, restoration, add-ons, premiums,
all of it explained in plain English.
And if you're still confused after this, just book a free call with our advisors at Ditto and we'll walk you through it calmly, no spam, no upselling.
The link is in the description.
Now, let's start with a quick snapshot of the insurer.
Care Health Insurance, formerly known as Religare, is a standalone health insurer launched in 2012.
It's promoted by Religare Enterprises, now controlled by Berman family of Darbu Group fame.
Now, their claim settlement ratio averages at 90% with an incurred claim ratio of 59%
and they've got a hospital network of over 11,400 hospitals across India.
Now, let's dive into the actual plan that is CareSupreme.
Now, who can buy this?
Let's talk about the entry age.
Adults 18 years and above can get CareSupreme.
For children though, it's starting from 90 days to 24 years
with an option for lifelong renewability.
Now, let's look at coverage options.
You can buy it as an individual plan or as a family floater
for up to two adults and two children.
The different sum and short options are 5 lakh, 7 lakh, 10 lakh,
15 lakh, 25 lakh, 50 lakh and 1 crore rupees. The policy tenure can be 1, 2 or 3 years.
Now let's talk about the basis. There's no copayment, no room rent restriction, no
disease-wise sublimit, pre and post 60 and 180 days respectively, daycare and modern
treatments covered up to some insured domiciliary and IH treatment covered up to some insured organ donor expenses covered up to some insured ambulance 10 rupees for some insured below 15 lakh and full some insured for
15 lakh and above. Now let's talk about restoration benefit because this is one of the strongest
features of Care Supreme. You get unlimited restoration triggered on partial or complete
exhaustion and valid for both same and different illnesses. So you're never left uncovered within
a policy year no matter how many claims you make. The bonus structure is also very strong. You get
50% bonus per year up to a max of 100% of your base sum insured and here's the kicker,
this bonus is retained even if you claim, that is very rare. But it gets better with
cumulative bonus super add-on which lets your base sum insured grow by 100% per year up to 500%
max and even better, this bonus never reduces even after claims. Now let's talk about the
waiting periods. Initial waiting period is 30 days except for accidents, specific illness waiting
period is 2 years and pre-existing illnesses waiting period is 3 years. There's also a detailed
list of specific illnesses that fall under the 2-year waiting period. This includes arthritis,
hernia, cataract, hysterectomy, kidney stones, fibroids, A&T surgeries and a lot more. Now,
what makes Care Supreme really good is because of their add-ons. Now, here are some add-ons that
are available and good. Cumulative bonus super. It takes your bonus from 100% to 500%. Claims
don't reduce it, must have if you are opting for a lower base Summon Shot.
Second is the Claim Shield. It covers 68 non-payable items like gloves, PPE kits etc up to full
Summon Shot. These small things often make up to 10-15% of your hospital bill, so this
add-on is practically a cost saver.
Third, Wellness Benefit. You can earn up to 30% renewal discount by tracking your daily
steps using fitness devices or apps It includes nutritional support digital fitness coaching and AI tracking Fourth Air Ambulance It covers medical evacuations up to 5 lakh rupees per year Works for emergencies when ground transport is not an option
There's also something called as a BFIT benefit.
Unlimited gym access via partner fitness centres.
Bookable via their app.
It's available for anyone aged 12 and above.
Next up is the Annual Health Checkup.
This starts from day 31.
Available once per year.
It covers routine panels.
No claims needed to access it.
The next is Instant Cover. It reduces PED waiting period to just 30 days for diabetes, hypertension, high cholesterol and asthma.
Next up, Modified PED Waiting Period. You can choose to bring down your PED wait time from 3 years to either 1 year or 2 years depending on the condition.
There is also an OPD add-on wherein you can get reimbursed Rs. 4,000 per person per year.
And this includes 4 GP consultations that is Rs. 500 per visit, 4 specialist consultations that is also Rs. 500 per visit.
all on reimbursement basis. Now let's talk about some discounts that CareSupreme offers.
15% by employee or promoter, tenure discounts of 7.5% on 2-year term, 10% on 3-year term,
family discount of 5% for 2-3 members, 10% for 4 members plus, direct channel discount up to 10%,
renewal discount up to 2.5% for renewal within 30 days, 5% if renewed earlier. Now let's talk money.
What does it actually cost? Now here are a few profiles on your screen. All premiums are inclusive
of GST and 5% digital discount and you can feel free to pause as well and take a look at the premium chart.
Now let talk about the premium structure and honestly this is one of the most smartest parts of the Care Supreme plan Unlike a lot of plans where the low premium is just bait and you discover restrictions later here the pricing actually reflects real usable features The base premium includes all essential covers and then you have the flexibility to add or skip certain
benefits based on your life stage. For young buyers, this works beautifully. You can get a
one crore cover at under 19,000 a year with bonus boosters and air ambulance included, which is
practically unmatched. That said, for older age groups, say above 60, the premium jumps sharply.
And in many cases, Care mandates certain add-ons like Wellness or Air Ambulance depending on your
age, which limits how much you can strip down the cost. But overall, if you're in your 20s to early
40s, Care Supreme is aggressively priced without cutting corners and that's rare in health insurance.
So, what's the conclusion? Care Supreme is a genuinely impressive plan. Flexible, customizable
and extremely value-driven. It gives you strong base features, no caps or hidden restrictions,
and the kind of restoration and bonus structure that rivals even premium price plans. Yes,
there are some limitations like slightly higher complaint volumes and mandatory add-ons for some
people, but overall, it's one of the best balanced plans in the market today. It works especially
well for young buyers in their 20s and 30s, families who want strong coverage with affordability,
anyone with pre-existing conditions who want shorter wait times. So folks, if you're still
unsure whether Care Supreme is the best plan for your situation, don't guess.
Book a free call with Ditto, we'll help you compare it with other plans like Aditya Birla,
HDFC Ergo or Nevabupa based on your exact profile. And no, we won't upsell anything,
we'll just explain, the link is in the description, our services are completely free.
If you found this breakdown helpful, drop a like, hit subscribe and share this with someone
buying insurance in 2025. I'll catch you in the next one, until then, happy insurance hunting.