Hi folks, welcome to Ditto Insurance. I am Shashank, your host, and joining me is our
senior advisor, Supreet. Hey, good to be here. Supreet here has advised 4,000 people. Thank
you so much for being here. Now, Supreet, let me tell you this. You guys have always
told me that get a term insurance because it is beneficial for your family if something
happens in a longer run agreed I get a term insurance now I am the one who's paying the
premium every year say 10-15,000 every year it's financially a burden for me man okay and
I wanted to see if there is an investment opportunity wherein I could get some money
back and make the term insurance work for me so what I did was I went on and searched
any such policies that exist and one thing that pop up was money back policy now money back policy
seemed like a really great option because i get periodic payouts of x amount and also my
family is insured now this sounds like a great plan is there any reason why you as a financial
advisor would say no don't go in for money back not just money back plans i think you can add few
more plans in the list okay your lip endowment okay return on premium plans okay uh so the thing
with these plans is they focus more on the return aspect okay now as an individual i would like to
ask you now what is your primary focus i want to cover my family so that when if i'm not around
they are insured they have enough money to live the way that they have been living with the current expense that we are incurring and adjusting to the future inflation they still covered Right So basically protection
Yes.
So if you are looking for protection, then choose an instrument that is purely giving
you that protection aspect, which is the term plan, where the premiums are lesser and you
can choose a higher cover amount and you said 10, 15,000.
that's closely around 1000-1500 rupees per month.
Right?
I don't think in today's world that should be burdening.
I think it's a couple of Zomato's bill anyway.
Right?
What do you think?
Right, right.
Now, you brought in the math here.
Help me break down money back's math.
Like, how does it work?
Right.
Let's take an example, right?
Now, let's say you have a money back plan.
You're paying a premium of around 50K.
Okay.
your sum insured is 10 lakh all right now keeping the return aspect aside first fall the question
is is 10 lakh enough to cover your family in your absence doing the math if suppose my expenses 50,000
now it can grow to 1 lakh say in 5 or 10 years now right and 12 months it becomes 12 lakhs I have
already exceeded that 10 lakh right yeah so not even one years of expenses in my opinion right
So, in order to chase that what do you do in order to correct it you try to get a higher
cover in the same plan.
Correct.
And then you end up paying lakhs in premiums towards it.
Okay.
Now when you look at the investment component of the same plan now when you calculate the
return on investment it is not even close to any of your SIPs today.
So the advice is now keep your insurance product different keep your investment product different
let there not be any conflict.
So the advantage of doing so while choosing your term plan you can choose a higher cover that is tailor made for you based on your expenses and when you thinking investment maybe you can choose a
pure investment instrument like say mutual funds or something.
But money back policy offers a periodic payout in five year gaps.
Now I read about this breakdown where suppose if I have a 65,000 annual premium I am insured
for 10 lakh rupees, right? And every five years, I get 15-20% of the sum insured which is one and
a half lakh every five years. Now, don't you think that I can use that one and a half lakh rupees
for my short term financial goals? You can. I mean, if you're looking at it from an investment
point of view, maybe it makes sense. But my question is, are you looking at it from an
insurance point of view? So what is the sum assured associated with that? Right. Again,
we circle back to the same thing that the cover isn't enough and the premiums, right?
So we want to compare and contrast maybe with our best plan that we suggest everyone and
a random money back policy.
So how do the premiums compare against each other?
Right.
Let me take your own example.
You mentioned 65K premium, right?
So if you want to break it down, you can probably dedicate 10, 15,000, which can get you about
a crore cover and the rest, you can invest it.
You can have an investment specific product and you can expect a return of say 10-12%
on your good days and I think this strategy would be much better than trying to get both
these components into one single product.
You don't get the best of either worlds end of the day.
Understood So finally what does Ditto recommend So we here at Ditto we advise on insurance right So we look at all the products from the insurance point of view Right Thereby recommending a term plan a pure term plan instead of these plans where there is a return component
Understood.
In fact, even in term insurance, there are return on premium add-ons that are available wherein you can pay in slightly higher premiums and get those options added.
Okay.
If you call Ditto, I think the first thing they would say is, please don't go for that.
I mean, it's easy to sell.
It's easy to say that, hey, you know, if you're not here, your insurance cover reaches your family.
Correct.
But if you survive, you get some money back, right?
I can easily convince somebody to buy those plans.
But I wouldn't recommend that to a family member.
So neither would I recommend to our clients as well.
Understood.
Folks, this is what Ditto is about.
We only and only give you the best advice because we have a stellar rating of 4.9 over 5 and we're backed by Zerodha.
We believe in a no-spam policy and we want the best for you.
Now, if you're in the market on a lookout for a term plan or a health plan,
then please don't hesitate to book a free of cost consultation call with our advisors.
The link is in the description.
Supreet, you have opened my eyes.
Again, time and again, you keep doing this.
Thank you so much for giving the breakdown on why money back policy might not be the best for me and for other folks out there.
Now folks, if you have any questions, please feel free to drop them in the comment box below and Supreet himself will be able to answer them.
Thank you.
Now, thank you so much Supreet for spending your time with us.
And folks, like always, like, share and subscribe.
Happy insurance hunting.