Cashless Everywhere.
One of the biggest announcements of 2024 and it came out of nowhere.
It's getting everyone excited.
So, in this video, we will explain what Cashless Everywhere means,
how you can benefit from this and why there is one big problem
that could mean an existential crisis for the entire scheme.
So, let's get started.
First things first, what is Cashless Everywhere?
So, right now, if you have a health insurance policy
and you have to make a claim,
you can do it in two ways.
The first is called the Cashless Procedure.
This means you go to a hospital,
you give them your policy document or your policy number
and you tell them what problem you have and then you just chill.
Because in the backend, the hospital will take care of everything.
They will take your policy number,
intimate the insurance company about your admission
and they will make a claim on your behalf for the medical procedure.
The insurance company will look at the details of your procedure
and pre-approve a claim saying they'll pay the 2 lakhs,
for instance, Manlo,
that will cost to fix your broken shoulder,
if you have a broken shoulder, that is.
This way, you won't have to pay a single penny from your pocket.
You don't even have to worry about all the medical documents
and submit them to the insurance company
because the hospital will do it for you.
So, once again, the premise is very simple.
You can just chill, get your procedure done
and walk out of the hospital without worrying about documents
or paying a single penny out of pocket.
This is great.
However, most claims aren't processed this way.
They happen on a reimbursement basis,
which means first, you pay for your medical procedure,
broken shoulder, out of pocket,
then you submit all your medical bills and documents
to the insurance company
and then you wait for them to pay you back,
which can take a while, by the way.
So, clearly, out of reimbursement and cashless claim,
cashless claim is the way to go.
But the only problem is that you can only make cashless claims
in certain specific hospitals.
Every insurance company ties up with some hospitals
that they call network hospitals.
So, if you visit a network hospital,
you can make a cashless claim.
If not, then reimbursement is your only option.
Obviously, this has been a big problem for the industry.
And that's why a few weeks ago,
all the general insurance companies,
health insurance companies came together
and said that you can now make a cashless claim in any hospital
even if it's not included in the M-Panel list of cashless hospitals
for your insurer.
And this is cashless everywhere.
So, how will this work?
Very simple.
If it's a planned procedure, like say a cataract surgery or something,
you have to inform the insurance company
two days in advance before admission
that you will be making a cashless everywhere claim.
And if it's an emergency
and you don't have time to intimidate the insurance company,
then you can do it within two days of admission.
Once you intimidate the insurance company,
they will share an MOU, a Memorandum of Understanding,
with the hospital regarding the rates, procedures, etc.
And if your claim is legitimate,
then the insurance company will pre-approve the claim.
This is like cashless only,
but you can do it in any hospital,
whether it's a network hospital or not.
Ultimately, you will have to pay no money
or very little money out of pocket
and the claim will be approved on a cashless basis.
That's the promise, at least on paper.
And this looks like a fabulous initiative.
It's also a real pain point
that so many customers have had for so many years.
This whole business of tracking network hospitals
and only visiting these hospitals for cashless claims.
In fact, this is a problem that we've encountered at Ditto,
making sure that we tell customers
to track network hospitals
and make sure they only visit those hospitals
if they have to make a cashless claim.
Now, with cashless everywhere,
all these problems are solved and customers should be happy.
Except there is one big issue,
and that is the hospitals are not very happy with this scheme.
In fact, the Indian Medical Association Hospital Board of India
has issued an advisory
warning all its members to not accept cashless everywhere
in its current format.
They're basically saying,
do not accept cashless everywhere claims
because this could put you out of business.
You meaning the hospital.
And this comes as a shock to many people
who are celebrating this cashless everywhere come-o.
And hospitals actually have their own reasons
for not being very happy with this move.
So let me explain this by actually explaining
how currently cashless claims are processed in network hospitals.
Right now, an insurance company will go to a hospital
and tell them that they will include their facility
in the cashless network in their empaneled list
if they give them a package deal or discount.
To give you a simple example,
if the hospital says a total knee replacement
will cost 1.5 lakhs for cash paying customers,
then the insurer will ask for a discount package
to settle the bill on a cashless basis.
Say they'll ask for a 1 lakh quote as opposed to 1.50 lakhs.
So 50,000 cut discount.
And if the hospital agrees,
then they will be included in the empaneled list.
And many people who own that insurance policy
may visit their facility
because now they offer cashless benefit.
As a result, the hospital gets better footfall,
more people coming in,
and the insurer can settle the bill at a discounted rate.
So everybody wins.
However, if the insurance company and the hospital
cannot agree on a standard rate,
then the hospital will not be included
in the empaneled list of cashless hospital.
So the hospital will lose out on the extra footfall,
but that's okay because they don't want to offer the discount
and they don't mind losing the footfall
because from this one insurance company,
how many people will come?
And the thing is,
different insurance companies
negotiate different rates with hospitals.
Private insurance companies
usually can negotiate a 10-12% discount on the actual rate.
But the public sector insurers
usually get a better discount.
Some 20-25%.
This is because public sector insurance companies
have a lot of customers.
They insure a lot of people.
So if you're a hospital owner
and you are not on their empaneled list
of cashless hospitals,
then you could lose out on all these customers.
Also, they can negotiate better
because they do it together in a group called Jipsa.
So they have even higher bargaining power.
Anyway, the problem with cashless everywhere
is that the current notification
asks insurers to get the most economical rate
while pre-approving claims.
Meaning, if some hospital has entered into an agreement
with public sector insurers
to offer a 30% discount on the actual rate,
then every insurer, whether public or private,
will offer the lowest rate
prior to authorizing a claim
using cashless everywhere scheme.
So basically, the insurance companies are saying,
this is the lowest discounted rate
that you will provide to us.
And this is the only way cashless everywhere will work.
So hospitals are naturally saying,
sir, we cannot offer this discount to every insurer
who wants to process a cashless claim
because if we did, we will go broke.
We can offer it to some public insurers
because they bring in so many customers,
but some random insurer who I've never heard of,
you're asking me to offer such deep discounts
to this guy too under cashless everywhere?
Why? What is the point?
In fact, in the advisory, the Hospital Board of India
has even attached the actual rate
according to their calculations,
which hospitals should be charging,
versus the expected rate insurers are likely to offer.
And the difference in rates, as you can see,
it's laughable even.
There's like a 5X difference in some cases.
So yeah, irrespective of who's right in this debate
in the current format,
it seems that there will be a lot of resistance
from hospitals to accept cashless everywhere.
They will most likely not accept these rates.
And this leaves us with one big question.
What should customers do?
Our advice is very simple.
In our opinion, Ditto's opinion,
this will probably take a while to solve.
It's not like they won't solve it, right?
But before cashless everywhere
begins to start working consistently,
I think the best option is to still consider
network hospitals before you buy an insurance policy.
If an insurance company already lists a hospital
in their M-Panel list of cashless hospitals,
it means the negotiation about rates are complete.
They've already agreed on the package.
So there won't be any issue for customers
on that front at least.
Yes, it's possible that the insurance company
may deny your cashless claim for whatever reason,
but at least the hospital will not have an issue.
So yes, cashless everywhere is an amazing scheme.
However, for the time being,
I think it's still important for you
to probably visit a network hospital
as opposed to any hospital
and hope that the cashless everywhere scheme works
because we are not entirely sure how this scheme will evolve
in the few weeks coming ahead.
Also, if you're looking to buy a health insurance policy,
don't forget to check out the link in the description box
at Ditto because we have Iridai certified advisors
who won't just tell you the headline,
but also explain everything that goes on behind the headline
like this cashless everywhere scheme.
So if you haven't done it already,
visit the description box, book a call with Ditto
and get the best advice for you and your family
when buying health and term insurance for free.
Also, if you like this video,
like always leave an actual like on the video
and comment your thoughts
about this cashless everywhere scheme, right?
Like if you know of anyone
who's actually made a claim under this scheme
and whether you think it will actually work
and we'll be really interested to hear all your thoughts
and we'll try and reply to as many comments as possible.
Like always, I hope you liked this video
and enjoyed this video
and until then, happy insurance hunting.