You just bought health insurance thinking it'll cover your hospital bills, but during
a claim, you're suddenly told, sir, there's a copay clause, or ma'am, your policy has
a 2 lakh deductible, and now you're paying out of your own pocket, confused, angry, and
wondering what just happened.
And if you don't want to be in such a situation, this video is for you.
Welcome to Health Insurance 101 by Ditto, where we simplify health insurance basics
like no one does, so you can always stay informed.
I am Shashank and we are here to simplify two often misunderstood clauses in health insurance,
copay and deductible. If you've never heard of these terms or have seen them in your policy
but didn't understand what they meant, this one's for you. And hey, if you're not sure whether your
current policy has a copay or deductible clause, you can always book a free call with Ditto's
advisors. We'll break it down for you. No spam, no pressure. The link is in the description.
Now, let's begin with a situation that you might have encountered. Let's say your insurance agent
tells you this, sir, we can reduce your premiums from 12,000 rupees to just 8,000 rupees if
you're okay with a small 20% copay.
Now what is copay?
It is a clause when you agree to pay a certain percentage of the hospital bill from your own pocket every time you make a claim Just means that you splitting 20 of your bill every single time You think it just 20 right not a big deal
and you go ahead with the policy. Now fast forward a year your hospitalized for an unexpected surgery
and the bill comes to 3 lakh rupees. You pull out your policy thinking glad I got an insurance and
it's all covered but then comes the bill in your hand and it says you have a 20% copay which means
now you have to pay 60,000 rupees out of your own pocket and the insurer pays only 2,40,000.
Now, ask yourself, was saving 4,000 on your premiums worth paying 60,000 rupees during
a medical emergency? That's the problem with copay. It looks harmless when you're buying the
policy, but it hurts when you actually use it. Oh, and it's not a one-time cost. It applies
to every claim, every time. But wait, not all copays are the same. There are different types.
Age-based co-pay, usually found in senior citizen plans because insurers see older individuals as higher risk.
It ensures some cost-sharing but can lead to heavy out-of-pocket payments for the elderly who need insurance the most.
Treatment-specific co-pay, applied only on high-cost or planned treatments like cataract surgery, knee replacement or organ transplants.
Insurers do this to avoid covering expensive elective procedures immediately after policy purchase Zonal co if you buy a policy in a small city but get treated in a metro this kicks in because treatment costs are higher in big cities insurers shift some of that burden to you hospital
based copay applies when you go to a non-network or premium hospital not tied up with your insurer
since costs there are harder for insurance to control they make you share the expense so always
check where the copy applies because sometimes it might only apply under specific scenarios
now let's talk about deductibles and health insurance a deductible is a fixed amount you
must pay first and then your insurance kicks in. It's like a mandatory fee that you need to pay to
make sure your health insurance plan unlocks. Now, unlike copay, which is a person-based,
deductibles are flat rupee-based. For example, if your policy has a Rs 20,000 deductible and
your hospital bill is Rs 1,000,000, you first pay Rs 20,000 and your insurer covers the remaining
Rs 80,000. Now, there are two common types of deductibles. One, per-claim deductible, which is
applied on every claim individually. If your deductible is 2 lakh rupees and you make a claim
of 1.5 lakh rupees, the insurer pays nothing. Only if a single claim exceeds 2 lakh rupees will they
cover the extra. Second is the aggregate deductible. This one adds up all your claims in a year. Once
your total out expense crosses the deductible limit the insurer starts paying Way more practical if you have frequent hospital visits or base policy already Aggregate deductibles are commonly found in super top plans while per deductibles are seen in regular top plans
Why do insurers include these?
Two main reasons.
To reduce premium costs for you and to prevent misuse of health insurance
for non-essential or inflated treatments.
In fact, some insurers offer these as options,
letting you voluntarily choose a copay or deductible clause to lower your premium.
Just be sure you understand what you're agreeing to.
Should you offer a plan with copay or deductible?
Well, if you're a senior citizen or have many PEDs, copay might be unavoidable.
And that's okay.
Some coverage is better than none.
If you're younger, consider a deductible-based super top-up.
It's an excellent way to get a higher sum insured and a much lower premium.
And between the two, deductibles are better because you know your max liability and can plan for it.
Also, pro tip, most comprehensive retail policies nowadays don't include copay or deductible clauses at all.
So always check your policy wordings before you buy.
And if you want help picking the right plan based on your health status and budget,
you know what to do.
Book a free call with Ditto.
We'll help you make sense of it all.
In the next episode, we'll be talking about disease by sublimits
and why this one small clause can be a big headache.
If this video helped you, share it with a friend or a family member.
Let's keep making India more insurance aware.
Happy insurance hunting!