Wait, you're telling me I can get unlimited doctor consultations, 24x7 personal medical
support, free diagnostic tests and a 1 crore insurance cover all in one plan?
Sounds more like a subscription to a luxury wellness service than health insurance, right?
Well, that's what Even Health Insurance claims to offer.
Yes, that's the name of the company.
Even.
Even Health Insurance.
But here's the catch.
Even isn't even an insurance company.
So what are you actually buying?
Hi folks, I'm Shashank from Ditto and in today's video, we're breaking down Even Health
Insurance, what it offers, how it works and who it's for and more importantly, whether
it's actually a good idea to buy it.
And by the way, if you'd rather just talk to an expert instead of figuring it out all
by yourself, book a free call with Ditto.
We'll help you pick the right plan.
Links in the description.
So first, let's get this out of the way.
What is Even?
is not a licensed insurance company. It's actually a healthcare provider based in Bengaluru. Think of
them as clinical services company that also bundles insurance in the background. This company was
launched in 2020 by a team of founders, Mayank Banerjee, Matilda Giglio and Alessandro Lallango
and is backed by Alpha Wave. Their model is simple. They give you unlimited consultations
with doctors support from wellness coaches chronic disease management and 24 bar 7 personal and they bundle this with a group health insurance policy via Magma hdi now how does this actually work even works through a corporate agency that called houston insurance advisors
private limited which is iidi registered so the insurance part is legal and valid but it's offered
as a group plan not as an individual retail policy so you're not the policy holder even as you're
a member under the group umbrella which has some advantages but also some pretty big limitations
let's talk about what you actually get even offers three tiers of membership plan care essential and
plus even care is the most basic no insurance just online consultations with doctors and access to
their medical team 24 7. even essential adds in group insurance so now you get hospital coverage
too but no diagnostics or advanced features. Even Plus is a full package, includes up to
1 crore insurance per family, cashless hospitalization, COVID-19 cover, free diagnostic
consultations, emergency care. Well, sounds amazing, right? Let's actually look at the pros.
First, the preventive care angle is brilliant. You get access to general physicians, specialists,
nutritionists, psychologists anytime you want. So you're not waiting for a health problem to
to become serious.
You're managing your health actively.
Second, the integration of services is seamless.
Diagnostics, consultations and hospitalization, it's all handled in one place.
You don have to run between hospitals TPA insurer and back And third the pricing is quite reasonable for what included especially if you actually use the services often But here where the red flags begin
Even doesn't sell individual policy.
The insurance you get is a group cover, controlled entirely by Even.
You don't own the policy, you're just a member.
That means you can't customize your plan.
You don't get lifelong renewability,
and if Even decides to change their partnership with Magma HDI,
your cover could change too.
Now, that's a big deal.
Also, you can't port this policy if you leave.
You're not the policyholder, so portability doesn't apply.
You're essentially on a subscription model,
and if they shut down, your cover may disappear with them.
Second issue, limited physical presence.
Even only has offline clinics primarily in Bengaluru,
although they are expanding this network.
Yes, consultations are available online across India,
but if you're someone who prefers walking into a clinic,
this might be a limitation.
And third, coverage gaps.
The group insurance via Magma HDI might not offer the same level of depth as a good retail policy.
Things like bonus, organ transplants, maternity, advanced surgeries may have limits or exclusions that aren't obvious out front.
So, if you're someone who values long-term stability or wants a policy you can truly own and manage, even may not be the right bet.
Now, let's compare this with traditional health insurance plans in 2025.
With a good retail plan say Cash Supreme Neewa Bhopa Aspire or HDFC you the policy holder You can choose your sum insured and features like OPT or maternity reduce waiting periods and most importantly you can port your plan renew it lifelong
and manage it on your own terms.
Even doesn't give you that kind of flexibility.
But it's also not trying to be that.
Even is designed for people
who want full-stack healthcare access
and want someone else to handle all the logistics.
Think urban working professionals
who are tired of running from doctor to lab,
to hospital to tpa so if you value that convenience and don't mind the group insurance limitations
even could be a fit but still if you are unsure here's what you should do book a call with ditto
and we'll help you understand whether even is right for you or if you're better off with a
more traditional plan the link is in the description even health insurance is not
really insurance in the traditional sense it's a hybrid product a mix of telemedicine
diagnostics and group cover. That's great for everyday health support and preventive care.
But if your priority is a long-term protection, customization and flexibility, maternity,
tax benefits or portability, you're better off with a retail plan. In fact, many people buy both,
even for day-to-day health and a traditional policy for serious medical emergencies.
But again, it all depends on your goals and that's what we're here for. Book a free call with Ditto
and we'll help you get it right.
The link is in the description.
Thanks for watching, folks.
So stay smart and stay covered
and I will see you in the next one.
Happy insurance hunting.