Okay, imagine this. A young couple, both 30 years old, bought health insurance right after their
wedding. They disclosed everything they could remember. But they forgot to mention that five
years ago, one of them had a mild seasonal allergy for a few months. Fast forward four years, one of
them needs a big surgery, a big claim. Now, normally you'd think, oh no, the insurer's going
to dig into their old reports, find that untreated allergy history and reject the claim. But surprise,
the insurer honor the claim fully, no arguments, no blame games. And the reason behind it? A little
known but very powerful rule called the moratorium period. Hi folks, I'm Shank and you're watching
Ditto Insurance. And today, I'm breaking down everything you need to know about moratorium
period, why it matters, how it works, and how it can literally save you during your claim time.
And if you ever feel overwhelmed by insurers fine print, or you just want to get a human being to
explain your options without any spam, book a free call with Ditto, the links in the description.
Alright, let's now get into it. First up, what is moratorium period in health insurance?
The moratorium period is a special protection built into your health insurance policy. It says
once you've completed five continuous years with a policy, your insurer cannot deny any future
claims just because of non-disclosure or misrepresentation of medical facts at the
time of buying unless it's proven that you committed a fraud. Meaning after five years,
your insurer cannot pull out old forgotten illnesses, minor non-disclosures or missed
surgeries to reject your claims. It's like a full forgiveness shield, protecting honest
policyholders who may have made genuine mistakes when signing up. Now, what counts as a fraud
though? Fraud includes acts like saying something is true when you know it's not, hiding facts you
knew were important, any act meant to deceive the insurer or anything the law clearly defines
as fraudulent. But here's the good news. The insurer cannot reject your claim or cancel
your benefits on grounds of fraud if you can prove that you genuinely believe the information
you gave was true there was no intention to hide or mislead and the insurer already knew or should have known the facts that you didn disclose The onus or the burden of proving fraud lies with the insurer then That means it the insurance company responsibility to show with evidence
that the policyholder or claimant deliberately gave false information
or hid important facts with the intent to deceive them.
This is also backed by IDI guidelines and various judicial rulings in India.
Insurers cannot arbitrarily reject claims by simply alleging fraud.
fraud, they must provide clear proof that misstatement or omission was intentional and
it directly influenced the insurer's decision to issue the policy or pay the claim.
If the policyholder can demonstrate that the mistake was genuine and made in good faith
and there was no intent to cheat, then it does not amount to fraud and the claim cannot
be denied on that basis.
Now how long does the moratorium period last?
Simple answer, once you cross 5 continuous years with your insurer, the moratorium period
It kicks in and protects you for the entire lifetime of that policy.
You don't have to apply for it, you don't have to pay extra for it, it happens automatically.
The moratorium period was initially set at 8 years under IRDI's 2020 guideline.
However, in a significant move to enhance consumer protection and simplify claims, the
IRDI reduced the moratorium period to 5 years in its revised master circular issued in April
2024.
Now, you might be thinking, isn't this the same as the waiting period?
Well, nope. Here's the difference.
Waiting periods are conditions that limit specific types of claims for a fixed time,
like you can't claim for cataract surgery or knee replacements for 2 years,
or you have to wait 3 years for pre-existing disease coverage.
Moratorium period, on the other hand, has nothing to do with the specific illnesses or treatment types.
It is purely about protecting you from claim rejections because of missed disclosures after 5 years.
You could still have a waiting period for knee surgery even after moratorium kicks in, if your policy says so.
But your insurer cannot deny a genuine hospitalization claim
just because you forgot to mention mild asthma from 10 years ago.
Under the latest IDIS guidelines,
policyholders can now carry forward their moratorium period benefits not just when migrating to another policy within the same insurer but also when porting to a completely different insurer That means if you have completed say three years under your current policy and decide to port or migrate that credit doesn go to
waste. The remaining two years to complete the five-year moratorium can continue from where
you left off as long as the porting or migration is done seamlessly and without a break. This is
a big win for long-term policyholders as earlier porting or switching policies would reset the
moratorium period. Now, your past coverage tenure, claim for years, waiting period credits,
and moratorium progress all move with you. Still, at Ditto, we always say don't casually
port your policy for small premium savings or minor features. Sometimes staying put is the
smarter and safer play. And hey, if you're wondering whether you should port or stay,
just book a free call with us. We'll guide you properly based on your specific situation.
The link's in the description. Now, let's take a step back and ask,
why do we need moratorium period in health insurance? Because let's face it, when you
buy insurance, you're filling forms, answering medical questions, trying to remember every tiny
doctor visit you've ever had. It's super easy to miss small details without any bad intention.
The moratorium period acknowledges that. It builds a fairness clause into your contract. It says,
if you paid premiums diligently, stuck with your insurer, and being honest, after five years,
your insurer should stop harping on your old paperwork. It levels the playing field and it
builds real long-term trust. And of course, there are huge benefits of moratorium period.
First, peace of mind. You're not spending years worrying whether some old surgery you forgot
about will bite you later. Second, stronger claim certainty. Once you cross five years,
your insurer's ability to challenge claims reduces significantly. Third, you build stronger
continuity benefits. Policies with long unbroken tenures naturally become stronger because of the
moratorium, meaning you should ideally nurture your policy like an asset and not keep hopping
around every few years. But as with all things insurance, there are also common myths about
moratorium period.
Myth 1.
Oh, I can hide my illnesses and be safe after 5 years.
Absolutely wrong.
If you knowingly hide a major illness that clear fraud and fraud claims can be rejected even after 10 years Myth 2 Moratorium covers everything even waiting periods Wrong again Waiting periods for diseases are separate and operate differently
Myth 3. If I forgot to renew, I still get moratorium benefits.
No. If you miss your renewal grace period and your policy lapses, your moratorium is gone.
You have to start again from scratch.
Now, for anyone wondering, how do I manage the moratorium period effectively?
It's actually simple. Listen.
First, buy the right policy with full honesty and complete disclosure to the best of your knowledge.
Second, renew on time every time.
Set reminders if you have to.
Third, if your insurer offers you upgrades,
opting for higher sum insured or adding super top-ups can be smart moves.
But keep in mind, any increase in coverage may come with its own fresh monitoring period
that applies to the enhanced amount.
And please, think carefully before porting.
If you really need to port, do it with the right advice, not just for the random discounts.
And this brings me to the next important thing.
Why choose Ditto for navigating the moratorium period in health insurance?
Because we actually explain this stuff to you,
not after the claim, but before you even buy the policy.
We make sure you disclose everything properly,
help you pick policies that match your health history
and guide you on how to maintain continuity the smart way.
We're not here to sell you shiny plans.
We're here to protect your future.
And again, our services are completely free.
Book a free call.
The link's in the description.
So finally, what's the conclusion?
The moratorium clause is one of the best consumer protection in health insurance today,
but it only works if you understand it and manage it carefully. It rewards you for honesty,
patience, and good financial discipline. Five years might seem like a long time,
but in the grand scheme of life, it's nothing compared to the security and peace of mind you
want. Protect your policy, protect your future. And if you ever need a guide on this journey,
Ditto's always here. Thanks for tuning in folks, and if you found this video helpful, hit like,
subscribe to our channel, and share this with anyone who has a health policy
or is thinking about getting one because trust me knowing about moratorium can make all the
difference between claim being paid and claim being rejected see in the next one
until then happy insurance hunting