With healthcare costs skyrocketing, who'll take care of India's low-income communities?
No need to fear, India's government health insurance schemes are here.
Welcome to Ditto Insurance.
My name is Tyra and today we'll be talking about India's top government health insurance
schemes.
But first, let's start with the basics.
What are the benefits of health insurance?
Firstly, it provides you with financial security against medical expenses, especially when
it comes to cost-free critical illnesses. It also provides coverage for pre- and post-hospitalization
costs, doctors' fees, and medications. Do note that this varies by scheme. It enables
cashless treatments at network hospitals the availability of this might differ from policy
to policy and you can receive tax benefits under Section 80D, but this may not apply
to all government schemes. Now, what is a government health insurance
scheme? It's basically a health insurance policy provided by the central or state government
government of India. Okay, but why are they required? These schemes are mainly for the
rural population and people who live below the poverty line, because they are the ones who don't
have access to high-quality medical facilities. As a result, they resort to cheaper options that
barely provide coverage or remedial measures. Also, even if they want to opt for comprehensive
healthcare, it would consume a huge amount of their income and savings. But with government
health insurance, both at central and state level, they'll receive the right funding to meet their
healthcare requirements. Alright, before we delve into the nitty-gritties, let me tell you a little
about us here at Ditto. We're an insurance advisory platform built by FinShots, India's
favorite new age newsletter. We provide honest and spam-free advice about health and term insurance.
We've helped over 3 lakh customers and we will never push you to buy. But if you do choose to
buy from us, we'll be there from start to end and stand by you through the entire claim settlement
process. We're available on call, so talk to us at the link in the description. Also, we are hiring
insurance advisory team members. This job is work from home with no sales targets. Check out more
about the role and apply in the link in description. Now, let's compare regular health insurance plans
with government health insurance schemes. In terms of eligibility criteria, for health insurance
plans, anyone is eligible for the same, regardless of their employment and financial status. Whereas,
for government health insurance plans, most schemes are only available to the low-income
community. After all, it was mainly made for them. In terms of some insured, health insurance plans
can have coverages up to 1 crore and above, but for government health insurance schemes,
coverage goes up to max 5 lakhs. Looking at purchase availability, health insurance plans
provide immediate policy purchases both online and offline. You also have the freedom to visit
the website and buy it yourself. Whereas for government health insurance schemes, there's a
longer purchase time because of the multiple steps and numerous documents to be submitted to avail
the scheme. With health insurance plans, domiciliary coverage is more or less available to the policy
holder, depending on the plan they have availed. However, there is no domiciliary coverage available
under government health insurance schemes. In terms of renewing the policy, for health insurance plans,
it's a very quick and easy online process. But for government health insurance schemes, doing it
online may or may not be an option. Moving on to network hospitals, health insurance plans usually
have providers working with the best private hospitals for treatment. Government health
insurance schemes include both public and private hospitals in their network. Under health insurance
plans, no claim bonus is available and may extend from 10% to 200% or may go even higher depending
on your policy. Tax benefits are available under section 80D, as I mentioned earlier, and free
annual health checkups are available as well, but may vary based on the policy you purchase.
These three features however are not available under government health insurance schemes And And finally our last feature to compare claim settlement Claim settlement under health insurance plans usually take less time than under government health insurance schemes Now coming to what
we have all been waiting for, the top government health insurance schemes. Starting with the
central government schemes. First, we have the Ayushman Bharat Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana.
This policy's purpose is to match the medical expenditure requirement of the bottom 40% of
the population. The eligibility criteria for this policy are the income of the family and
individuals. The coverage this policy offers is max rupees 5 lakh. This scheme covers three days
of hospitalization charges and 15 days of post-hospitalization expense. This plan also
covers all pre-existing diseases with no waiting period for the same. Policyholders also get to
enjoy the perks of cashless treatment at network hospitals and additional coverage for ICU charges,
doctors' fees, prescription medicines, and more. The annual premium for this policy is just Rs. 30.
Next, we're looking at the Employee State Insurance Scheme. This scheme is designed
for factory workers earning a max of Rs. 21,000 as a monthly wage, Rs. 25,000 for workers with
disabilities. This scheme's purpose is to help these workers meet medical expenses in case of
accidents or occupational hazards. This plan requires an equal part payment towards the
premium to be made by the employer and the employee, except in the case of workers earning
less than Rs 137 per day, in which the employer pays the entire premium. The plan is extended to
the employee and his or her family and offers a sickness benefit of up to 91 days per year and an
extended sickness benefit of up to 2 years in the case of malignant or long-term ailments.
This scheme also offers a disability benefit, a 26-week maternity benefit and a dependence
benefit due to the workplace hazard. We then have the Pradhan Mantri Suraksha Bhima Yojana.
This scheme is an initiative to boost insurance penetration in India.
The scheme aims to offer funds to its policyholders in the case of accidental disability and or death.
The plan also offers a coverage of Rs 2 lakhs in the case of complete accidental disability or death
and 1 lakh in the case of partial disability.
All that the policyholder needs to avail of this scheme is their Aadhaar card
and a bank account from which the premium for this will be automatically deducted.
Coming to the Rashtriya Swastika Bhima Yojana,
This government scheme protects individuals working in unorganized sectors across India.
This scheme offers Rs 30,000 for workers and their families to cover the expenses for hospitalization,
treatment of diseases and transportation, which is capped at Rs 1,000.
By paying a premium of Rs 30 per year, the plan offers cashless benefits too.
As for the Janani Suraksha Yojana,
this is a maternity health insurance policy that aims to ensure healthy pregnancy treatments
are available for both mothers and newborns.
The targeted market in this case is expecting women who are economically disabled or dependent
and need the funding to undergo a healthy delivery.
This scheme covers the delivery process as well as post-delivery care assistance.
Policy holders get completely free treatment in government hospitals along with some cash assistance.
For low-performing states, Rs 2,000 or Rs 700 and for high-performing states, Rs 1,200 or Rs 600.
This is based on whether they are located in rural areas or urban ones.
Our last central government scheme to be discussed is the Universal Health Insurance Scheme.
This scheme is like the government's version of a family floater health insurance plan.
It offers medical coverage for the entire family, especially those who are economically disabled.
This policy covers medical expenses for the entire family up to Rs 30,000.
It also covers expenses related to the doctor's consultation fees, hospitalisation, maternity, room rent and medical supply.
This policy also offers a cover of up to Rs 25 in case of accidental death Let move on to the state government schemes Starting with Maharashtra Mahatma Jyotibha Phool Jan Arogya Yojana which is a scheme designed by
the Maharashtrian government for those living below the poverty line. The cashless benefit of
this scheme can be availed by the underprivileged. This includes families. So that includes those
with an Anapurna ration card, Antyodiya Ana Yojana ration card, a yellow, orange or red ration card
holder, residents of government, Mahila ashrams and senior citizen homes and children living in
government orphanages. This plan extends its coverage to the entire family of the policyholder
and this scheme offers a sum insured of Rs 2.5 lakhs in case of renal transplants and Rs 1.5
lakhs for hospitalization expense. Next, we have Rajasthan's Bhamasha Swastia Bhima Yojana.
This scheme is for Rajasthan's rural population as well as the beneficiaries under the National
Food Security Act and the Rashtriya Swastia Bhima Yojana. This scheme is a comprehensive
health insurance plan with a host of features and perks for policyholders, such as pre- and
post-hospitalization coverage for 7 and 15 days respectively, some insured of Rs 3 lakhs for
critical ailments, coverage of Rs 30,000 for general illnesses, cashless treatment options,
and OPD treatment coverage. Then we have Tamil Nadu's Chief Minister's Comprehensive Insurance
scheme. This scheme is launched by the Tamil Nadu government in association with United India
Insurance Company Limited. This scheme is a family floater health insurance policy offered
to individuals with an annual income of less than Rs 75,000. Under this scheme, individuals can
claim up to Rs 5 lakhs for hospitalization expenses and can opt to get treated in either private or
public healthcare facilities. This government health insurance scheme also offers to cover
1,000 plus medical procedures. The West Bengal Health Scheme, launched in 2008, offers financial
assistance to government employees and pensioners for any and all medical treatments. This scheme
can be an individual and family floater policy, depending on the requirements of the policyholder.
The sum insured offered under this policy is capped at Rs 1 lakh, which also covers OPD
treatments and medical surgeries. Coming to Karnataka's Yashaswini Health Insurance Scheme,
This scheme's purpose is to boost health and wellness across the state of Karnataka,
specifically for poor people and farmers.
This scheme will grant them access to quality healthcare services without it eating into their life savings.
This policy can be availed by any individual under 75 years of age
and offers coverage for 823 surgical procedures from close to 600 network hospitals.
Next, we have Mukhya Mantri Amrutam Yojana.
This is a family floater health insurance plan offered by Gujarat's state government
where the policyholder gets access to medical treatments across trusted public and private
hospitals without any financial strain. This scheme has a sum insured of up to Rs 3 lakhs,
catering to the medical requirements of the poor and low-income community.
We now have Kerala's Karonia Health Scheme, which is a critical illness health insurance cover for
those who have an annual income of less than Rs 3 lakhs. This scheme was designed to aid those
suffering from critical diseases like the ones listed on the slide. The Kerala government extends
adequate coverage of Rs 5 lakhs to fund these medical treatments. This coverage caters to
secondary and tertiary hospitalisation care. Policyholders can claim hospitalisation charges,
surgical charges, ICU room rents, medicine charges, crucial diagnostic tests and doctor's fees. All
they need with them is their medical history, Aadhaar card and income certificate to benefit
from this scheme. Now, coming to Andhra's Dr. YSR Aarogya Sri Healthcare Trust, which includes
four different health insurance schemes.
The Arogya Rakshya Scheme for those above the poverty line,
the Dr. YSR Arogya Sri Scheme for those below the poverty line,
the Employee Health Scheme for state government employees,
the Working Journalist Health Scheme which covers selected medical procedures This scheme is available both as individual health and as family floater plans This scheme offers coverage of Rs 5 lakhs per annum for the family This cover can be utilised for hospitalisation expenses cashless treatments
for 30 days after discharge for those undergoing therapy, treatment of pre-existing diseases,
post-hospitalisation treatment coverage for 20 days, follow-up treatments and check-ups.
It also offers outpatient care for its policyholders at government hospitals and health camps.
And finally, we have Telangana's State Government Employees and Journalists Health Scheme.
This scheme offers premium healthcare services to government employees and the state journalists.
This plan offers substantial coverage to meet the medical requirements for retired and current employees and pensioners of the state government.
This prevents them from using their savings for emergency medical requirements.
There is no upper limit for some insured and no contributions need to be made by either the pensioners or the employees.
Alright, now that we have explained each and every central and state government health insurance scheme, let me tell you about some of their caveats.
Firstly, in terms of coverage, government health insurance schemes provide very little coverage that often falls short of the medical treatment charges.
Additionally, unlike the best health insurance policies, these schemes come with disease-wise sublimits and caps on procedures and features.
This means you might be looking at a substantial expenditure from your personal savings to deal with medical costs.
Also, some government health insurance policies do not offer funding for certain ailments and procedures.
Government insurance schemes are only available in certain regions, states, or nations.
Provider network limitations.
Government schemes have a limited network of doctors, hospitals, and healthcare providers.
This makes it difficult for policyholders to enjoy cashless benefits.
Eligibility limitations.
Government health insurance schemes demand certain criteria to be met by an individual for enrollment.
This includes citizenship, employment, age, etc.
Waiting periods
A majority of public health insurance plans have a waiting period before certain perks and coverages can be accessed by the policyholder.
And finally, claim settlements
Generally, the claim settlement time for government health insurance schemes is much higher than regular health insurance plans.
Okay, so why should you consider regular health insurance alongside government schemes?
For enhanced coverage
Regular health insurance plans offer higher sum insured, wider coverage for procedures
and other benefits like OPD, maternity, ponies, restoration, etc.
For wider network
Regular health insurance plans provide access to a broader network of hospitals
both public and private for cashless treatment
For flexibility
With regular health insurance plans, there is more flexibility in plan selection
based on your specific needs and budget.
For renewal convenience, easier online renewals for continued coverage
is an added benefit with regular health insurance policies.
For the waiting period, most regular health insurance plans
have paid add-ons available to reduce the waiting period.
For claim settlement, as seen earlier,
one of the greatest benefits of having a regular health insurance plan
is that the claims are settled in less time than government health insurance claims.
So, what does Ditto think?
Government health insurance schemes definitely play a vital role in making healthcare more
accessible for low-income families. However, their limitations are that they may not provide
complete protection. And so, exploring regular health insurance plans alongside these schemes
can offer a more comprehensive safety net against rising medical costs.
So yeah, to know more or find the plan that's best for you, you can talk to Ditto's IRDAI
certified insurance advisors for free. I promise that you won't be spammed nor forced to buy a
plan. Talk to us at the link in the description. Till then, like, share and subscribe. Happy
insurance hunting!