During COVID-19, hospitals were full.
People with serious illnesses had no choice but to get treated at home.
But here's the big question.
Can your health insurance cover treatments done at home?
The answer is yes.
But only if you know about domiciliary hospitalization.
Hi everyone, I'm Shashank and you're watching Ditto Insurance.
And in this episode of Health Insurance 101,
we'll explain when and how you can claim insurance for treatments done at home
and why it's not as simple as it sounds.
And hey, if you want someone to check your policy
and tell you if this benefit is included,
you can book a free call with Ditto.
Link is in the description.
What is domiciliary hospitalization?
It refers to a medical treatment for an illness
that would normally require hospitalization
but is instead done at home due to many reasons.
The patient being too unwell to move
or no hospital beds being available.
Think of it as hospital-level care at home
under medical supervision.
See, it's not the same as basic home care or hiring a nurse.
It has to meet some strict conditions.
Let's understand this with an example.
Mr. Sharma, who's aged 75, develops pneumonia during a COVID-19 wave.
No ICU beds are available.
A doctor recommends oxygen, IV fluids and continuous monitoring.
All this done at home.
Since this treatment would normally require hospitalization
and it's supported by doctor's notes and bills, it qualifies for domiciliary claim.
Now, when is it covered?
The treatment is for a condition that would usually need admission It lasts more than 3 days A doctor certifies hospitalization is needed All treatment is under a doctor supervision detailed records and bills are available But here the catch most insurers only reimburse these expenses no cashless option
Many common illnesses are excluded like asthma, diabetes, bronchitis, cold and flu, psychiatric issues etc.
So always check your policy to know is domiciliary care covered, what diseases are excluded,
Are pre and post hospitalization expenses included?
Is there a sublimit or duration rule?
Now, domiciliary versus home health care.
Don't confuse the two.
Domiciliary, it's done at home because you can't be moved or there's no hospital bed available.
And this is usually reimbursed.
Home health care, it's done at home too, but by choice, but pre-approved by insurer.
This is often cashless through network providers and not all insurers offer this.
A couple of final tips before we close the video.
Keep doctor's prescription and treatment summary ready.
Maintain daily treatment records signed by a doctor.
Submit all bills and documents on time.
And what is the bottom line?
Dormitory cover is a lifesaver in emergencies,
especially for elderly patients or during hospital shortages.
But it only works if your policy supports it and your paperwork is perfect.
So if you want help checking whether your policy offers this benefit,
book a free call with Ditto.
No jargon, no pressure.
And in the next episode, we'll cover cumulative bonuses.
how your sum and chart grows every year and what happens when you make a claim.
So folks, if this video helped you, share it with someone caring for elderly parents.
Happy insurance hunting!