Welcome to Ditto Insurance. My name is Kavya and today we'll be covering ICICI iProtect
Smart Term Plan, the features, costs, problems and who should buy it. So stay tuned and let's
begin. So who should consider this plan? See, if you want a reliable brand name with stable
performance, then obviously ICICI is a great option. This plan has a good number of add-ons
to make your plan more comprehensive. And they offer a zero cost option where you get your
premiums back if you give up the policy during a specific term. And it's a good plan at economical
premiums. Before we move to the features, how is ICICI doing compared to other players? Their
three-year claim settlement ratio is 97% which is less than other top players but still up to the
Their 3 year amount settlement ratio is 92%.
Now this means for every Rs 100 claim they pay out only Rs 92 which is also a good number.
Now coming to the volume of complaints.
As you can see their numbers is much higher than other players so it may be a cause of
concern for you.
Before we go ahead a little about Ditto.
We are an insurance advisory platform built by FinShot India favourite new age newsletter We provide honest and spam advice about health and term insurance We helped over 3 lakh customers First of all we will never push you to buy
You can take as much time as you want.
And if you do choose to buy from us,
we will guide you through the entire journey as well as the claim settlement process.
This way, you can sit back, take your time to weigh your options and buy when you want to buy.
We're available on calls as well as WhatsApp,
WhatsApp, so talk to us at the link in description. ICICI Protect has multiple variants based
on the add-ons you pick. Their entry age is 18-25, available terms are from 5 years to
85 years and their cover starts from 50 lakhs. Moreover, there are some more criteria that's
on your screen. Coming to the basic features. Here is a list of their top features and paid
add-ons, let's get into them one by one. Waiver of premiums is an inbuilt feature which allows you to
stop paying premiums in case of total disabilities. Critical illness benefit offers a lump sum payout
to you which is deducted from your cover. Now it covers 34 illnesses that's on your stream.
Another feature is zero cost benefit. So if your policy is a minimum of 25 years,
If you have more than 5 years left and you in your 60s you can surrender your plan and get back your premiums Life stage benefit offers you to increase your cover in case you start a family or for some any other reason but your premiums will increase too
Next we have the accidental death benefit add-on where you get an additional sum over your cover
in case of accidental demise. This is a good rider if you are a frequent traveler and you can get
some discounts too. Lastly we have terminal illness rider. Here in case you're diagnosed
with a terminal illness, ICICI gives you the whole cover for you to utilize. Now before we jump to
the costs, let's look at the payment terms. One is of course the regular premium. Next is limited pay
where you pay all your premiums in 5, 7, 10 or 15 parts or you pay only till you're 60 or you can
just pay for the whole thing one time. You can make your payments monthly, yearly, quarterly or
half yearly. Moving on to the costs. Now, the premiums depend on gender and whether you're
a smoker. We have compared the premiums with HTFC Click to Protect Super and Max Life Elite.
The premiums are on your screen. As you can see, the premiums are pretty economical compared to
the other two plans. So, what are the problems? First, the critical illness rider could be a
problem because the amount is deducted from the cover and other plans in the market might not cut it from the cover at the same price Some insurers also cover critical illness as well as accidental disability under the waiver of premiums which is more beneficial
And lastly, ICICI prudential is not serviceable in a few PIN codes due to restrictions.
So now that is done, what does Ditto think?
See, this is one of the best in the market owing to the brand's value and performance.
But are there any alternatives?
Depends on what you want.
If you are looking for a simple base plan, then ICICI EyeProtect Smart is a good option.
But if you are looking for add-ons like Critical Illness Without Deductions or a better waiver of premiums option that covers both Critical Illness and Accidental Permanent Disability,
you have good alternatives like HDFC Click to Protect Super, MaxLife Smart Secure Elite or Tata AI Sampoorna Raksha.
So, what do we recommend?
If you are looking for comprehensive riders, this might not be the best plan for you.
But if you're looking for a pure term plan, this is an economical plan from a good company.
Plus, the premiums are good for smoker profiles.
To know more or find the plan that's best for you, you can talk to Ditto's IRDI certified insurance advisors for free.
I promise that you won't be spammed or forced to buy. Talk to us at the link in description.
Till then, like, share and subscribe. Happy insurance hunting!