For the past few weeks, ICICI Lombard General Insurance has constantly been the talk of the town.
Now, although Lombard is not a partner at Ditto, we'd like to do an honest analysis of how good is
it as an insurance company. First of all, ICICI Lombard is a general insurance company, which
means they have many types of insurance like travel insurance, health insurance, etc. This
means that they would have a limited number of plans compared to a standalone health insurance
company like Care. Now, ICICI Lombard was established in 2001. It is a joint venture
between ICICI Bank with 64% stake and Fairfax Financial Holdings Limited, a Toronto-based
financial services company. So basically, ICICI Lombard has been in the market for two decades
now. So how is it doing? Now before we go ahead, a little about Ditto. We're an insurance advisory
platform built by FinShots, India's favourite New Age newsletter. To date, we've advised
over 3 lakh people and we provide honest or spam-free advice about health and term insurance.
First of all we will never push you to buy You can take as much time as you want And if you do choose to buy from us we will guide you through the entire journey as well as the claim settlement process This way you can sit back take your time to weigh your options and buy when you want to buy
We are available on calls as well as WhatsApp. Talk to us at the link in description.
Coming to ICICI Lombard's operational metrics.
Looking at the last three years, we can see that their claim settlement ratio has ranged around 85%
while the industry average has been around 90. Basically, they're only settling 85 claims per
100 and that's pretty low. I mean, at Ditto, we recommend a CSR of above 90. So, ICICI is
falling short. Now, let's see the incurred claim ratio. This has stayed around 85% over the years,
which is more or less around the industry average. So, works well. This means they're
paying the claims as well as making money. They have a network of 7,500 plus cashless hospitals
and centers. Now this is again less given the industry average is around 9100.
Lastly, we've got complaint volumes and this is where ICICI is neck to neck with HDFC.
In the last three years, they've received seven to eight complaints for every 10,000
claims which is insanely low This proves that their service and operations team is pretty efficient But also given it a general insurance company their health insurance number could be averaged
out over the other products. So all in all, it's a decent insurance company. So why haven't we
partnered with ICICI Lombard? Before I answer that, let me tell you about ICICI Lombard's top
plans. Health Advantage, which is one of the most comprehensive plans in the market. It offers great
features like only 2 year waiting period for PEDs, restoration, alternative treatments covered,
and no unnecessary room rent or disease-wise limits. Moreover, it covers animal bite vaccinations,
bariatric treatments, and international treatments too. However, it offers a very low loyalty bonus.
Another good plan is Health Elite Plus, which has similar features as Advantage. However,
However, it has room rent limits, sublimits on catracks and very low loyalty bonus.
Then we have iHealth+.
It also has a 2-year PD waiting period, no room rent restriction, alternative treatments
covered.
Plus, it offers OPD and maternity cover.
But it also has disease sublimits very very low loyalty bonus and restrictions on restoration Lastly we have Health which is slightly cheaper than iHealth The features are also similar So why haven we partnered with ICICI Lombard
See, ICICI Lombard is a decent pick as a provider.
But when we give recommendations, we are transparent about the insurers' metrics.
And the first thing people look at is CSR.
Everyone knows what CSR is.
So, given that their CSR is kinda low, it can be a turn off for some people.
Network hospitals, another word everyone has probably heard.
That's also low here.
However, we should not forget that ICICI is exceptional with its complaint volumes.
In fact, their plans also have great features.
So, if you're someone who trusts ICICI as a brand, then you can easily consider it.
However, if an insurance company's operational metrics are important to you and their low
No numbers bother you, you can check out other insurers in the market.
We have reviewed HTFC, Care, Niva Bhopa, Aditya Birla and Ako on our channel too.
The links are in the description.
Also, if you are looking for any health or term insurance related advice, book a call
with us at the link in description.
It's all free.
Till then, like, share and subscribe.
Happy insurance hunting.