Welcome to Ditto Insurance. My name is Kavya and today we'll be reviewing ICICI Prudential Life Insurance Company.
The company's metrics, their top plans, the features, costs and all. So stay tuned and let's begin with the background history.
It was established in 2000 as a joint venture between ICICI Bank and Prudential Corporation Holdings.
So basically, they've been around for more than 2 decades.
It's one of the top 3 private players with max life and HDFC life.
So, how is it doing?
Now, before we go ahead, a little about Ditto.
We are an insurance advisory platform built by FinShots, India's favorite new age newsletter.
To date, we've advised over 3 lakh people and we provide honest or spam-free advice about health and term insurance.
First of all, we will never push you to buy.
You can take as much time as you want.
And if you do choose to buy from us, we will guide you through the entire journey as well as the claim settlement process.
This way, you can sit back, take your time to weigh your options and buy when you want to buy.
We are available on calls, so talk to us at the link in description.
Also, we are hiring for insurance advisory team members.
It's a work from home role with no sales targets and no prior experience needed.
Apply at the link in description.
Coming to ICICI Prudential's operational metrics. Look at the last three years, they've been
settling 97 of the claims it receives which may be slightly less for term insurance but still pretty reliable Now let see the amount settlement ratio which stands at 92 This means for every Rs 100
claimed, they give out Rs. 92. But this doesn't mean that all claims are partially given. It's
just a ratio of the total amount of money given versus total amount claimed in a year. Lastly,
we've got the complaint volumes. In the last 3 years, they've received 14 complaints for every
10,000 claims, which is more than its competitors. But the industry average is 72. So, pretty less
still and stats a good thing. So, all in all, it's a decent insurance company. Let me tell you
ICI Prudential's plan options. They offer many types of life insurance plans such as simple
term plans, ULIPs, insurance for children, etc. At Ditto, we believe in keeping insurance and
investment separate. So, we will look at the term insurance plans offered by ICICI.
They have two variants, ICICI iProtect Smart and iProtect Return of Premiums. We will look at both
the variants in short but we have done a detailed review of iProtect Smart on our channel. The link
is in the description. Now, iProtect Smart is one of the best term plans in the market because
it's comprehensive, affordable and it has the best riders to choose from. The list of both inbuilt
riders and add-ons is on your screen. Now look at the most popular riders in the market. You can see
that iPretect has them except for the option to change your cover or get monetary benefits in case of total permanent disability So what are the drawbacks Though ICICI offers many add and flexible zero options major add like Waiver
of Premiums and Critical Illness have a few limitations.
Waiver of Premiums in iProtect only happens in case of accidental total permanent disabilities,
but other players also include critical illnesses.
Although ICICI covers a good number of illnesses, the critical illness payout is deducted from your base sum assured.
So, is iPretect worth the money?
Not if you're looking for riders like waiver of premiums or critical illness cover.
But if you want a pure term plan at economical rates and from a good company, this is a good option.
Plus, it's affordable for smokers.
Coming to iPretect return of premiums plan.
First, what is return of premiums?
Basically, you get your premiums back when the plan matures.
But this plan would cost you double the premiums for a simple term plan.
But it's not even worth the money because there is barely any interest on the returned
money and it doesn't even beat inflation.
So we don't often recommend a return of premiums plan at Ditto.
However, let's check it out.
iProtect Drop offers three variants.
One is return of premiums where you get back your premiums when the plan ends.
Second is income benefit which means you get back premiums in form of regular income once
you turn 60.
Third is life stage cover where your summer short increases by 5 every year till age 55 Maximum it can get is double and you get the premiums back after maturity This plan doesn offer any inbuilt add like waiver of premiums
terminal illness etc. but you can get some add-ons like critical illness cover and accidental death
benefit. Here is a list of riders available and not available in iProtect TROP. Now let's compare
the premiums of iProtect Smart and iProtect TROP. You can see that the premiums for TROP are
actually double and as we discussed not worth the returns. Now double premiums and no value for
money. It's best to go for a simple term plan with required riders. We have done a detailed review of
iProtect Smart on our channel. The link is in the description. And if you have to get your premiums
back, you can choose the zero-cost option in iProtect Smart.
Apart from that, is there any problem with ICICI Prudential as a company?
Yes, it's not serviceable in a few Indian PIN codes.
So, what does Ditto recommend?
Well, ICICI Prudential as a company is great, no doubt.
And if you're looking for a term plan with them, iProtect Smart might be a good pick.
Check our review of iProtect Smart on our channel.
The link is in the description.
To know more or find the plan that's best for you, you can talk to Ditto's IRDA certified insurance advisors for free.
I promise you that you won't be spammed or forced to buy a plan.
So talk to us at the link in description.
Till then, like, share and subscribe.
Happy insurance hunting.