You've got that amazing corporate health insurance, right?
The kind that doesn't ask questions, has zero waiting periods,
and feels like the best part of the job.
You feel like you've got it all covered,
until one day, you think about quitting.
So, what happens then?
Hi there folks, welcome back to Ditto Insurance.
If you're new here, I'm Shashank from Ditto.
And in today's video, we talk about something that doesn't get enough attention.
How to convert your corporate health insurance into a personal individual plan.
Here's what you can expect from this video.
We'll break down what corporate cover really offers,
why it may not be enough,
when and how to switch over to an individual plan,
and the benefits you carry forward during the transition.
And by the end, you'll have a clarity on whether making this shift makes sense for you or not.
And hey, if you want someone to walk you through your options personally,
you can book a free call with Ditto's advisors.
We'll help you make sense of your health insurance one-on-one.
The link is in the description.
And yes, our services are completely free of cost.
Alright, let's start with the basics.
No points for guessing.
Corporate health insurance is usually provided by your employer.
It's easy, doesn't need any medical tests, has no waiting periods,
and often includes family coverage as well.
Sounds amazing, right?
But here's the catch.
It's tied to your job.
The moment you leave or retire, it's gone.
and that leaves you vulnerable unless you have a backup.
So, when should you consider switching from corporate to an individual plan?
And more importantly, is it even possible?
Yes, it is.
According to IRDAI guidelines,
you can migrate from your corporate health insurance to an individual policy But there a condition It depends on whether your insurer allows it in the first place so you need to check with your hr or insurer first now let me walk you through the
actual steps of converting your corporate health insurance into your individual one step one
confirm if your insurer allows migration not all do so this is very crucial step two
Put in your request before leaving the job, ideally at least 30 to 45 days in advance.
This gives everyone enough time to process the switch.
Step 3. Review and compare the plans your insurer offers.
Even though you'll stick to the same insurer, you might have options with different benefits.
Choose one that works for you.
Step 4. Submit the paperwork.
This includes your policy details, claim history, KYC documents and a resignation letter or proof of your last working day.
Step 5, pay the premium for your new individual plan.
And Step 6, once everything checks out, your insurer will issue the new policy and you will receive confirmation with the continuity benefits.
Now, if you are thinking, wait, what continuity benefits?
Well, here's the thing.
If you've already served part of waiting periods under your corporate plan, that counts.
Let's say your corporate plan had a 3-year waiting period for a health condition
and you've already done 2 years,
in the new individual policy, you'll only need to wait for one more year.
Now, that is a huge win.
Now, quick reminder, if you want help comparing plans, understanding paperwork
or even knowing if your insurer allows the switch, you can book a free call with Ditto.
Our advisors are IRDI certified and will help explain everything in simple plain language.
The link is in the description.
Now here are a few things you should absolutely keep in mind before porting One see timing is everything You must request a conversion within the insurer deadline usually before your last working day
2. You must stay with the same insurer while migrating.
That is why it's called migrating and not porting.
3. Benefits like waiting period credits and bonuses may carry forward,
but check this beforehand.
4. Coverage may differ.
Corporate plans are cheaper because your employer chips in,
but they often come with limited flexibility.
Individual plans are more customizable and that brings us to our next point.
Let me give you a quick snapshot of how corporate and individual health insurance differ.
Now, I know you're going to tell me, Shashank, I know this,
but stick around and you'll know exactly why you need to have a retail plan.
Corporate health insurance is like group deal.
You get it because you're part of the company.
It usually kicks in from day one, sometimes covers dependents,
and the premiums are either fully or partially paid by your employer.
But what is the catch?
You have zero control over the coverage and it disappears the moment you leave the job.
Individual health insurance, on the other hand, is your personal plan.
You choose the summer insurer.
The benefits, the add-ons, basically it's built around your needs.
The premium might be higher, but the coverage stays with you.
Job or no job.
Plus, you can renew it for life, which makes it way more reliable in the longer run.
So, what are the actual advantages of converting to an individual plan?
First, you maintain continuous coverage.
No coverage gap when you leave your job or take a break.
Second, you don't lose progress on waiting periods for pre-existing diseases.
Third, you get flexibility.
Add riders like maternity, OPD or consumables cover
and choose a higher sum insured if you like.
And finally, you gain independence.
You don have to worry about what your employer decides about insurance anymore Now let say you convinced what are some good individual health insurance plans to consider in 2025 HDFC Ergo Optima Secure
is a solid option. It has no room rent limits, offers 100% registration benefits, which can be
converted to unlimited with an add-on and covers up to 2 crore rupees. Plus, it has a great claims
settlement record. Second, Care Supreme. It gives you unlimited registration and a total bonus of
up to 600% with an add-on.
Its hospital network is strong
and it's ideal for those looking for reliable coverage
with flexibility.
Third, Aditya Birla Active One Max
offers one of the highest renewal bonuses
up to 500%
and includes restoration benefits
unlimited times.
Perfect if you want long-term value
and a plan that grows with you.
This has cool booster plus feature
that carries forward unused coverage
and restoration that kicks in after the first claim.
ICC Lombard Elevate is a flexible plan
with solid features and 15 plus add-ons.
You can reduce a waiting period
or get unlimited bonus accumulation.
But remember, the best plan depends on your personal needs.
If you're unsure which one fits you best,
just book a call with us at Ditto.
We'll recommend a plan that's made for you
because not one size fits all.
All right, time to wrap up.
Corporate health insurance is a great benefit
while you're employed,
but don't rely on it for long haul.
If you're planning a job switch,
starting a business or retiring soon, start thinking about getting your own individual
health plan. It's your own safety net on your own terms. Thanks for watching folks. If this video
helped you out, don't forget to share it with someone who's thinking about leaving their job
soon. And if you still have questions, book a call with us. We'd love to help you out. The link
is in the description. I'll see you in the next one. Until then, happy insurance hunting.