You already know how term insurance works.
You pay the insurance company a small fee every year to protect your downside
and in the event of your passing, the insurance pays out a large sum of money to your family.
Today, I will tell you how you can enhance your base term policy
to increase its ability to protect you and your family better with something called as RIDERS.
By using...
PIZZAS!
Yep, I'm not kid...
Not kidding.
Your margarita is your base plan.
It covers your sum in short.
That's it.
Plain term plan.
Now, let's assume you want to enrich your plan.
This is where RIDERS come in.
You have several options in the market like...
Waiver of premium, critical illness, terminal illness, life stage benefit, zero cost option,
accidental death, accidental disability and so on.
And just like how not all toppings belong to your base plan...
Like your pineapple.
Not all RIDERS are necessary and recommended by us.
Let's say, accidental death rider.
By adding this rider to your base term insurance plan,
additional coverage is provided to the nominee the policy holder's death results from an accident.
This rider typically comes with a relatively affordable premium.
If you travel very frequently and seek additional accidental coverage,
opting for this very rider could be beneficial.
However, at Ditto, we advise choosing a sufficient base cover with a good summer shot
that provides coverage for all types of death, regardless of whether they are accidental or not.
Some insurers provide an extra benefit with the base cover of term insurance to address
total permanent disabilities and this is called income on permanent disability cover.
This additional benefit may be offered as a lump sum by some insurers,
while others provide it as a monthly income for up to 10 years,
following a total permanent disability diagnosis.
While the likelihood of experiencing permanent disabilities is low,
this add-on typically comes with an affordable premium.
According to Ditto, while it's not essential,
it could be beneficial to have this add-on for added financial security.
Now, there are some toppings, say like your onions, that are mostly on most of the pizzas
and just like that, life stage benefit may be a part of your plan.
With this rider, you can increase the summer shot later in life,
such as upon marriage or upon childbirth, when you have more number of dependents to look after.
Some insurers also provide voluntary top-up options,
allowing policyholders to increase coverage regardless of major life events.
ICICI iProtect Smart, Tata AI Sampoon Raksha Plus, HDFC Care to Protect Smart and Bajaj E-Touch
offer life stage benefits as inbuilt.
Max Life Smart Secure Plus offers top-up, but the plan is since discontinued and the current
step i.e. Smart Total Elite Protection offers neither top-up nor life stage.
Both life stage and top-ups are capped to a specific amount and subject to conditions,
and the premiums increase proportionally when the sum assured is increased.
There is also the zero cost option, in which you receive all premiums back at no additional expense.
Most leading term plans include the zero cost option, though it comes with very specific terms
and conditions that vary among insurers. These conditions typically specify the minimum
duration the policy must be held, conditions for exiting the plan and other factors.
Nevertheless, as an inbuilt feature, this zero cost option is beneficial to have
and provides flexibility to exit the plan if necessary.
HDFC Care to Protect Smart, ICICI iProtect Smart, Max Life Insurance, Smart Total Elite
Protection, and Bajaj Etouch offer it inbuilt.
Lastly, there is Terminal Illness. This is when a medical practitioner believes that a person is
going to die within six months due to any terminal illness, and the insurer will release the sum
insured to the holder and the family upon the certification from the medical practitioner.
However, the likelihood of a medical practitioner issuing such a certification is relatively low.
While the rider may not seem practical, it is an inbuilt feature with most of the plans which comes
free of cost. HDFC Care to Protect Smart, ICICI iProtect Smart, Max Life Insurance,
Smart Total Elite Protection, Bajaj Etouch, and Tata AI Sampoona Raksha Plus, and MRSS offer it
inbuilt. And finally, let's come to two riders that are highly recommended and that you should
have. You see, life is really unpredictable, just like how the pizzas on my table are, and there are
numerous illnesses on rice. God forbid someone gets cancer and they're not able to work, there is no
income, then who will look after the family? That is where the critical illness rider comes in.
The critical illness feature provides a lump sum payout upon diagnosis of any critical illness.
Specified in the policy document, this amount can be utilized without any restrictions imposed by
the insurer. Policyholders can use it for income replacement or to cover additional medical expenses
arising from the critical illness. Although you can argue that the cost of the medical expenses
can be taken care by comprehensive health insurance, critical illness feature is still useful
as an income replacement during tough times. There is another rider which is a cost-effective
option and has beneficial additions to a term insurance policy considering its price and
functioning. At Ditto, we strongly recommend this rider to be included in the term plan. This is
waiver of premium. This feature ensures that all future premiums are waived off if the policyholder
is diagnosed with a critical illness or suffers from total permanent disability, mostly due to an
accident as specified in the policy document. Some term plans cover both critical illness and total
permanent disabilities due to accidents, while others only cover total permanent disabilities
due to accidents or terminal illness. Now you see you can always opt in for a pure margarita pizza
that is a base plan with inbuilt riders, but then you always have the option to enhance it with
several other toppings which are not here or riders in our case. These riders are good to
have and not needed than not to have and need it. Now that's all folks see you in the next one and
happy insurance hunting!