Today we're looking into SBI Life Insurance, one of the biggest names in India's insurance landscape.
They offer four distinctive term plans, each designed to cater to different needs,
lifestyles and financial goals. Whether you're looking for basic coverage or more personalized
protection with advanced customization options, SBI Life has something for everyone. By the end
of the video, you'll know which plan could be the best fit for you. Before we dive into the plans,
let's look at their performance. With a claim settlement ratio of 98.62% for 2023-24 and
annual business reaching 38,238 crores, they're a solid player in the market, right up there with
other major players like HDFC Life and MaxLife. The annual business demonstrates SBI Life's strong
market presence and operational efficiency which are important factors to consider when choosing
a term plan. When comparing term plans with other players like HDFC Life and Max Life, this figure
can signal how well the insurer is equipped to honour the claims and maintain financial health
over the time. Now, let's get into their four main term plans and examine them in detail.
First up is eShield Next, SBI's most comprehensive term plan. It has an extensive coverage with
multiple riders. It's also affordable and offers three cover options, level cover benefit,
the nominee receives a fixed sum assured upon the policyholder's death.
Increasing cover benefit.
The sum assured increases by 10% every 5 years
up to double the initial amount or until the policyholder turns 71.
And third, level cover with future-proofing benefit.
This allows increasing the cover amount during significant life events
without additional underwriting.
eShield Next also includes a terminal illness benefit inbuilt into the plan providing up to 2 crores if diagnosed with a terminal illness Let me explain this Say you diagnosed with a terminal illness benefit inbuilt into the plan providing up to 2 crores if diagnosed with a terminal illness Let me explain this Say you diagnosed with a terminal ailment
The doctors, one from your end and one from the insurer's team,
offer a written declaration of a poor prognosis with only a few months to live.
In this case, the insurer offers a sum of up to 2 crores to the policyholder,
provided the diagnosis is conducted within the policy tenure
or before the policyholder turns 80.
However, if the terminal illness amount is less than the base cover,
the balance is paid out in the event of the policyholder's death.
Also, this amount can be paid out as lump sum,
a monthly installment or a combination of a lump sum and a monthly installment.
There are other optional riders that you can select with this plan.
One is Better Half Benefit,
which provides 25 lakhs coverage for your spouse after your death.
This cover stays intact till the maturity year of the base plan as chosen by the primary policyholder.
Upon the diagnosis of terminal illness or in the event of the death of the spouse,
the insurer pays you 25 lakhs as a lump sum in the mode of a level cover
irrespective of the payment option chosen of the base policy.
Accidental death benefit, which we all know,
that is if the policyholder passes away within 120 days of the accident,
the insurer pays the accidental death benefit rider some assured to the nominee.
Accidental total and permanent disability benefit
If the policyholder is left totally and permanently disabled due to an accident,
the insurer offers an assured sum to the policyholder.
Next plan is a smart shield.
SBI's most popular term plan offering coverage from 25 lakhs to an amount determined by the underwriter.
There is an option to add a couple of riders and also customize your plan here Well it has two variants First level term assurance Here fixed death benefit is equal to the chosen sum assured Both riders are capped at 50 lakh rupees and cannot exceed the base sum assured
SmartShield is a popular plan because it is simpler, much more affordable,
making it appealing to people who want a basic, cost-effective term insurance
without extra frills.
Whereas eShield Next that we discussed before this offers increasing coverage,
life-stage milestone boosts, future-proofing and flexible payout options,
making it ideal for someone with evolving financial needs over time.
So if you're someone who wants a no-frills plan with minimal investment but decent protection,
we suggest you to go with SmartShield.
But if you want long-term, adaptable coverage that increases as your responsibilities would grow,
then eShield Next is your better bet.
Moving on, catering to the low-income population, SBI Life also has a Grameen Bhima Pure Term Insurance Plan,
which is affordable while also offering lower range of coverage, extending from Rs. 10,000 to Rs. 50,000.
While there is the standard death benefit perk available under this plan, there are no other riders available,
and the only mode of premium payment available is a single-time payment
since the premiums are as low as Rs. 300 up to a maximum of Rs. 2000 only.
Lastly, we have Aarogya Shield, a unique combination of pure term and health insurance
from their SBI General Insurance.
The term insurance component offers coverage from Rs. 5 lakh to Rs. 2.5 crores.
It provides death benefit with no riders
and the health insurance component includes coverage from 1 lakh rupees to 3 lakhs
and it covers OPD in admission costs daycare treatments ambulance charges pre and post hospitalization expenses maternity charges hiv aids treatment costs and etc but note that there a two
waiting period for pre-existing conditions arogya shield by sbi is a plan which gives you coverage
for your health as well as term now we at ditto don't recommend such products because they might
not be a very good health insurance plan, neither a very good term plan. And we always recommend you
to go with pure term plan or pure health plan. Now let's compare SBI Life's premiums with
competitors. For a 1 crore term plan for 30 year old non-smoker male, here are your premiums.
Clearly, SBI's premiums are on the higher side when you compare it with other players like HDFC
Life, ICICI Prudential and Max Life. SBI Life is a major player in Indian life insurance market
with a scale comparable to HDFC Life. While their term plans are generally on the pricier side,
they lack certain key features that many buyers might be looking for. For example, SBI Life does
not offer critical illness coverage as an add-on, which provides additional payouts upon diagnosis
of conditions like cancer or heart attacks. Additionally, they don't have waiver of premium
add-on which waves off future premiums in case of critical illness or permanent disability.
That being said, SBI Life's claim settlement ratio is impressive, slightly above the industry
average at 97%. If you are looking for a reliable no-frills term plan with high CSR, then SBI Life
is a good option. Remember, the right term plan depends on your specific needs and budget. Always
compare multiple options before making a decision. Thanks for watching this detailed look at SBI
life's term plans. I'll see you in the next one. Happy insurance hunting.