Hi folks, welcome to Ditto Insurance. I'm Shashank, your host and today we are back
with yet another amazing video for you. This is one of those videos that you've been waiting
for and have asked us time and again. Well, Axis Max Life Insurance has released one of
their newest plans. It's a term plan and it has tons of features in it. Now, to discuss
this in detail, I have with me in the studio, Sushant, who is our Senior Program Manager
here at Ditto. So, I'll hand over the whole stage to you, the whole studio to you, because
I would love for you to take us over through all the variants and all the features and
how different Axis Max Life is doing with this STPP plan.
Okay, Percy, thanks for having me once again. It's quite an interesting plan. For the rest
of this video, the plan's name is Smart Term Plan Plus, but we'll be calling it STPP for
your sake of convenience. But yes, I think the interesting bit here that they've done
is the number of variants that they have. They're pretty much trying to cater to any
and every kind of requirement you could possibly have. They're also thinking of any possible
scenario. They're thinking of plans where you have more focus on an accident cover and
less on your initial death benefit. They have cases where in the initial few years, your
cover amount is really high, but after that it reduces. They have a type of plan where
you get back your money in between, towards the end and so on. So, I'll try my best to
simplify it and cover all of them in a brief, structured sort of way. But with that, let's
get started. Before we begin though, just to let everyone know, earlier in the previous
variant, Max Life used to offer a 12% discount in the first year for salaried customers.
In this plan, they've made it a 15% discount for the first year, which is a plus. But from
the second year onwards, in comparison to the previous plan, there's an increase of
about 2% to 4%. So, Max Life is getting a bit more expensive. But nonetheless, like
I mentioned, the features that they're offering do make a compelling case for the premiums
that they're charging. Perfect. So, I think with that, let's get started. The first one
would be our primary recommendation, the most basic balanced cover plan. This is your regular
old-term plan, right? There's really not much to it. The minimum age to buy this plan is
18, the maximum is 60. Cover amounts of your choosing, I think it starts at about 50 lakhs
and can go up to at least 20-30 crores. They offer payment in years, like you have a single
pay option where you can pay all your premiums within one year, or you can pay a limited
pay just for 5-10 years or even a regular pay. So, like I mentioned, this is a pretty
basic term plan. So, at least this variant of it is the basic term plan. So, I don't
want to dwell on this too much. The next one, which is a bit interesting, is called the
rebalancing cover if I'm not wrong. So, this is the second variant. It's not something
I would actively recommend, but no harm in simplifying it. So, how this works is your
term plan will have a split of 10% and 90%, meaning 10% of basic death cover, 90% accident
death cover. So, what this means is if I buy a 2-crore plan, my cover amount will start
off with 20 lakhs of death benefit and 1.8 crores of accidental death benefit. And over
the span of my entire term insurance, my accident cover will get rebalanced, wherein it will
go all the way down to zero and my main death benefit will go all the way up to 2 crores.
This might be helpful, like if I were to think about, right, that who are they trying to
cater to for this? Maybe that sector of audience whose lifestyle or hobbies are such, or maybe
their job right now such that they travel a lot. They're a lot more prone to accidents
and that's maybe the current scenario. But over the span of 20-30 years, as their career
progresses, as life progresses, they're planning to cut that down and focus more on the actual
death cover as opposed to the accident part. So, like I said, not a very common use case,
not something I think a lot of people would be rushing to buy, but it's still interesting
for them to have come up with something like this. Another point to note for this particular
plan and why I maybe do like it a little bit is the fact that underwriting will only happen
for 50% of the sum in short. So, let's say if I as an individual cannot buy more than
1 crore of term insurance, through this plan I can buy 2 crores actually. I need to be
just eligible for one and they'll give me two. But with the caveat that look I start
off with 20 lakhs of credit, death benefit and towards the end I eventually become eligible
for 2 crores. So, like I said, it's got a mix of features.
Do you see people getting this plan more than the basic plan?
Not really, no. Very rare case scenario.
Alright, Sushant, before we head to the third variant, I'd like to tell our audience a little
about Ditto. So folks, Ditto is an insurance advisory platform where you can get free health
or term insurance advice from experts like Sushant himself. We are backed by Zerota and
we have over 10,000 plus reviews on Google with an average of over 4.9. So, if you want
to compare two policies or if you want to renew your old one or if you want to port,
then we can help you for free. You can get our expert guidance for free with a link in
the description. All you need to go is go to the link, fill in the details and we will
assign an IRDI certified advisor to you under two minutes. With that said, Sushant, let's
get back.
Cool, so I think the third variant now is something called early return of premium.
Now this as the name suggests, if it has return of premium in it, Ditto is very against it
and for pretty obvious reasons. I think return of premium plans are never worth it. If you
actually calculate the financial outflow, meaning my basic term plan cost me 20,000
but the return of premium plan would cost me at least 30-35,000. Now that additional
outflow, instead of giving it to the insurance company, if I were to go and invest it even
in something as simple as an FD, I would make a lot more money by the end of this tenure.
The insurance company is simply going to pay me back all my premiums and nothing else.
So yeah, early return of premium is a bit interesting in the sense they don't give it
at the end of it. What they do is they give you 50% of your premiums once you turn 60
and the remaining 50% at the end of the policy tenure. So maybe they're just trying to do
something a bit different from the traditional ROP but nonetheless, like I said, it's not
something we would ever recommend or ever suggest. It really doesn't make financial
sense.
Right, makes sense. So now let's head to the fourth variant.
This I think is probably one of my favorites in this plan and it's also Ditto's secondary
recommendation after the primary most basic plan. This is the one I would probably go
on as a second benefit. So this one is actually called Smart Cover and this is Ditto's secondary
recommendation after the primary one being a balanced regular term plan. And I did kind
of like this plan. I thought it was interesting what they've done here. So what MaxLife is
essentially done here is that they're offering a plan where for the first 15 years of your
term insurance, your sum insured is boosted by 50%. So let's say if I bought a 2 crore
term plan, for the first 15 years I will have a 3 crore term plan. And after that for
the rest of my tenure, it will come back down to 2 crores.
Okay, this is interesting. Why do you think they're giving us an accelerated, you know,
higher sum insured?
So this I think is for people who have financial responsibilities right now. For example, you've
got a home loan running, you've got an education loan running, but you also foresee that look,
15 years later I'm building my savings and investments parallelly. 15 years later I might
not need this much term insurance or I might not have that extra 1 crore of financial liability.
So it depends on profile to profile. But like I said, broadly these are the ones we've seen
where people who have liabilities or responsibilities upfront, to them maybe it makes sense. But
I think the interesting part here was in case I buy a 3 crore plan directly versus this plan,
I will save about 20% in premiums.
So there's a reason why it's Dito's recommendation. In your eyes, why do you think it is one of
the recommendations? Do you think people should consider this?
Look, like I said, it's our secondary recommendation. It's never going to be my primary. I would
always still rely on our level term insurance cover, which in fact, we even help you arrive
at how much you need, right? We look at inflation, we have an NPV calculator that we help you
decide how much insurance you should take. This being a secondary recommendation, because
look, it's specific for people who are one, if you're confident on your financial planning,
like I said, you're sure that 15 years later, you will have the savings and investments
that you thought you would, right? Wherein you're providing the family the safety net
through that as well. And two, you're also confident that in 15 years, your liabilities
will be taken care of. The additional responsibilities you have right now will not be there 15 to
20 years later. Because once you buy this, the plan is going to, I mean, this reduction
will happen by default. It's not something that you can later tap out of saying, hey,
actually, can you give me three crore for life? They can't do that. You've opted for
that variant. Yeah, like I said, it's a recommendation, but a secondary recommendation.
I think we've gotten four in our basket up until now. And I already see a variation of
a return of premium, the basic plan, the basic plan with little toppings. I mean, I don't
think that there is anything more that Axis Max Life could do. Or do you want to prove
me wrong? They have a bit. Look, the next couple of variants are variations of ROP.
So I think I can just cover those quickly. We don't really recommend those. So I'll just
go over them real quick. So the next one is actually a combination of a whole life and
an ROP plan. A whole life plan meaning you buy a term insurance till the age of 99 or
100. So this one's till the age of 100. Now, this isn't like your traditional whole life
plans offered by, let's say, ICICI, Protector. I think even Bajaj Itaq has this option. This
isn't like that. This comes with a mandatory ROP option as well. So in this plan, 50% of
your premiums are paid after you turn 60. And the remaining 50% is paid in case you
live out until 100. And if not, then should someone pass away, let's say at 70 or 75,
his family will get the claim amount and the remaining 50% of his premiums. They will pay
that back. So this, like I said, it's a bit complicated in terms of this combination of
whole life and ROP. As a concept, these are two variants that I again would never genuinely
advise to someone, considering the caveats that they come with, the additional premium
you pay and just as a concept, right? I mean, buying a life insurance for a whole life is
kind of like trying to buy money back plan. And an insurer is aware of this. So they're
going to charge you exorbitant premiums to make sure that they're not just handing out
two, three crores of claims. They'll collect that much premium over a span invested and
make sure they have the money ready for you. So rather than that, why not buy a traditional
term plan and do your own investments on the side?
Exactly. I think a lot of people are unaware about the fact that, you know, whole life
insurance is very different from term insurance. So folks, if you are one of them, and if you
end up buying or even considering an option, the first option, in fact, which comes on
your Instagram ad or even your Facebook wall, so maybe, maybe halt and pause and come over
to Rito's channel. We have made tons of videos where we've explained why a whole life insurance
plan might not be the best one for you. Well, in any case, if you want a direct call with
us, then the link in the description is always open for you. Book a free call with us. And
let me remind you, it's a free call and we will help you find the best term plan for
you so that you can protect your family and live life brindas.
Now, Sushant, let's go over the last two variants. I'm pretty, I mean, I don't know what I would
call it. I'm looking forward to it.
Right. So the sixth variant again is a traditional ROP variant, Plain and Simple Return of Premium.
Not like the previous where there's a whole life or there's an early return. This is just
traditional return of premium. Again, I think the premiums itself will speak for themselves.
Let's say for 30 year old male was buying a 3 crore plan for a span of 30 years, so
till his age of 60. Traditionally, his term insurance should cost him about 30,000, but
under this variant, his plan will cost him 90,000. So that's a 200% traditional outflow
in premiums. And our logic is the same, right? That additional outflow, we're assuming you
have the money to spend, right? If you're buying a plan like this, you do have the 90,000.
So why not pay the insurance company 30 and diversify the remaining 60? Put some in an
FD, some mutual funds, buy some gold for your kids, whatever, right? Sky's the limit. So
you could do whatever you'd like with that. Perfect. So needless to say, this is not one
of our recommendations. Cool. So the last variant is called the income protection option.
Now, this one is more for the nominees wherein when the claim happens, should someone pass
away and his family applies for the claim, the money will be dispersed in an income form.
It won't be given to them as a lump sum. Now, right off the bat, this feature is something
that, look, we personally don't actively recommend because we would rather the family get the
entire lump sum, right? Reason being that they have control over such a large amount
wherein should they have some immediate lump sum expenses coming up? Should there be a
loan that's running and they wish to just simply clear it off? Should there be major
expenses coming up like kids' education, marriage, and so on? You'd like to have that lump sum
with you to pay these off, right? And two, even if there's an emergency in the future
and you need to sort of pay things off, it does help to have control over that two crores
Nonetheless, insurance companies do try and make it as lucrative as possible for them
as well. Some people, in fact, prefer this thing that, look, I'm not sure if my family
will be financially sensible or responsible enough to handle such a large amount. Even
there, I think, are sort of counter to that is, you know, you can simply just open a fixed
deposit in the bank. You walk into a bank and say, hey, I have two crore and just watch
the line that comes to you, right? The line of employees that's after you. But nonetheless,
So what they've done firstly is a level income option, where plain and simple, over a span
of 10 years at least, you can choose the span as well, but 10 years is the bare minimum,
they will disperse this amount in monthly income format. So 120 installments if I choose
10 years, that's what my two crore, three crore will be divided into and the family
will receive this. So the second part under this is called the inflation proof income
cover. So what they've done here is every three years, the income that your family is
getting will increase by 10% to kind of maybe combat some form of inflation, right? Although
10% every three years, I don't think is even CPI index, right? It's less than that. But
nonetheless, every three years, 10% of income, the income amount will increase. And this
is capped at 200% of the original income. So if the duration you've chosen is such
that where it can keep increasing every three, three, three years, after eventually when
your income reaches 200%, it will stop increasing, they'll just get a level amount. And this
as many would guess, this variant is more expensive than the level income variant, because
they are essentially offering a higher payout to your family, right? More than what you
kind of purchase. So accordingly, the premiums as well would be a bit more expensive.
Right.
All in all, just to summarize, I think going over all seven features briefly, there are
about three of them which are ROP related. So let's just skip those. There's this one,
which is the income format that your family receives. The main three that I would say
is Ditto's primary recommendation, a balance cover. Ditto's secondary recommendation,
which is the boost one, where for the first 15 years, you have a higher sum insured and
then it reduces. And the third one being the balancing one between a regular and an accident,
1090, which reduces eventually. These are, I think, just to summarize, these are the
variants offered by Max in this plan.
Perfect. Perfect. So I was just thinking while you were explaining it to me, obviously, there
are a couple of riders that you can have which will make your term plan even much better.
But I was just thinking if there are any inbuilt benefits or features that these plans have
that would make people turn their eye towards the STP plan.
Yeah, there are quite a few free benefits actually. I think Maxlife has always been
known for that, where apart from the riders, they do tend to offer a bunch of inbuilt features
and inbuilt add-ons. And I think that's what really sets them apart, right? At the end
of the day, why they're as popular as they are.
So a couple of basic ones that are from the previous plan as well. I'll just quickly go
over those. You have your Terminal Illness Benefit. This is, I think, where you get a
payout of up to one crore on diagnosis of a terminal illness. And upon demise, if there
is an additional amount, the balance amount is paid to the family.
The Cover Continuance Benefit. This gives you an option to defer your premium payments
by 12 months. Should you, let's say, be between jobs in the future, right? And you feel, hey,
I don't want to take on this financial responsibility as well. You can simply tell them that, hey,
I'll pay you next year. Just let me be this year.
Khatme likhna.
Yeah, exactly. So you do have to pay next year, of course. When you go back next year,
they will charge you double for the previous year and the current year. But it just offers
a bit of financial comfort to a person in a time of need. Then you have the Special
Exit Benefit, which is available after 30 years of policy completion and not in the
last four years. This, again, is a free of cost feature, right? Where whatever premiums
paid until then up to date, you'll get those back minus GST. So this is called Special
Exit or Early Exit, where should I wish to exit from my term plan earlier, not wait till
the completion? You can get back some money. And this is free of cost.
Another one that they've had from the previous variant is called the InstaClaim Payout, where
this is applicable after one year of policy completion. And they have different bands
for this, that if your covered amount is such, it's only so much. But just to give you a
rough perspective, in case someone's family applies for a claim, and it's been more than
a year since he purchased the plan, they will pay out a very small amount immediately that
day or the next day itself. And the balance amount will be processed after due process
and due diligence of the claims paperwork. This is a very normal amount, up to two lakhs
maximum. If your sum in short is lower, it could even be lower. Like I said, this is
the maximum that they offer. So nonetheless, this could help you with immediate expenses
that come up, maybe taking care of hospital bills in a time like that or anything at all.
So this does help out. So another one here is obviously the price difference between
male and female. Ideally how it was before in the insurance industry was that it was
never clearly defined as a percentage. This was a well-known fact that when you buy life
insurance of the same profile, male and female, same age, same everything, the prices were
different. Now by how much? Sometimes dependent on age and profile and everything. But often
a lot of brands have started standardizing the percentage. So it's now clear that it's
a 15% difference. If a male individual pays X amount, the female of the same age buying
everything else the same, she'll pay about 15% lesser. So that's an advantage that they
get because of mortality rates, plain and simple. A female's life expectancy is a lot
more than a male's. So accordingly, the risk for an insurance company is calculated accordingly.
Now there's a couple of free ones that again stood out to me and I thought they were unique
and I personally like them as well. So the first one is again related to female clients
specifically. It's called the Lifeline Plus Variant. So this one gives a female policy
holder the option to enhance her sum insured post her spouse's demise. Meaning in case
her spouse were to pass away. Ideally she does have more responsibilities on her now, right?
The kid is, you know, the kid's responsibilities, parents and laws, whatever it is. The financial
responsibilities do increase slightly. Therefore they give her the option to modify her existing
term plan itself and increase the cover amount by up to 50% or 50 lakh whichever is lower.
Now this can only be done after at least 3 years of holding the policy and 2 it has to
be done within 6 months to 2 years of the spouse's demise. So they will need proof
of this obviously and accordingly you can show them that hey this is the date it happened
and they'll give you this benefit. This is a well thought benefit. Exactly, I really
thought it was a thoughtful benefit. The last one now is again related to the special
exit benefit but this is specifically for customers who have chosen limited pay as their
payment option. Meaning you're not going to pay for the entire policy 10 years, you're
going to pay for just 5, 10, 15 years. Now what they've done is your regular special
exit plan where you exit the plan early at a predefined moment. You get back all your
premiums minus GST. Here again MaxLife has defined those moments. This might sound a
bit confusing but what they've essentially done is it's either at policy term minus
13 years meaning 13 years before your policy were to expire. So if it were to 70 at 57
is the benefit or its policy term minus 7 years. This depends profile to profile payment
and so on. So I think maybe for specific profiles that advisors can help. And the benefit here
is that you get 200% of your premiums. You don't just get back 100%. So let's say if
you paid them as total of about 5 lakhs you'll get back almost 10 lakhs. That's what you're
eligible for. Like I said the condition when you can get it, it's best you just get in
touch with our advisors and they'll probably guide you based on your profile. And to point
to note this is only available if you've chosen a limited pay. Which in fact is increasing
these days. We're seeing a trend where people are opting for limited pay more and more with
the logic that look the convenience factor of it. We just want to get this done within
5, 10 years. It's not about whether regular pay versus limited pay what makes more sense.
It's simply about not wanting to have such a long term financial commitment. So they're
okay with paying for 5, 10 years and wrapping this up, letting the policy continue and maybe
20, 30 years later Max Lef says hey would you like to exit and get back 200% of your
premiums. I mean who wouldn't want that? Exactly. It really might make sense to some profiles.
But yeah I think that summarizes the free features as well. Right those are some pretty
great in-bird features. Now I'm excited to see the paid add-ons. What do they look like?
Anything that stood out? So they have the traditional ones your waiver of premium, critical
illness, accidental death. So I'd rather not go into the specifics of those. I think we've
covered those a bunch of times. The one that stood out to me is again this has probably been
picked from like a health insurance plan. It's a maternity benefit. So again it's something specific
for female leads wherein you can claim up to 2 lakhs worth of maternity expenses. So here again
some conditions you have to be between 18 and 40 when you buy this plan. There's a 10 month
waiting period. So from the date of purchase of the plan you can exercise this benefit only after
10 months. That's when this benefit kicks in and this benefit is active only for the span of 5
years. The summer short that they're offering for this is 2 lakhs. Now this isn't bad I think in a
metro city like Bangalore, Delhi in most private hospitals I think maternity shouldn't cost more
than that 2-3 lakhs at most. And in fact in health insurance it's not a feature we recommend. We do
suggest that you rely on your corporate health insurance for this. And again I think we've done
a separate video on this too. But for someone to offer this within term insurance it's the first of
its kind and I do like this. Alright Sushant. Now I think this is the moment that everyone's
been waiting for. Pretty good variance, pretty good plan, pretty good riders that you have and
benefits all nailed. But how much is it going to cost us? So they're actually not bad. I think
Maxlife has always been known to offer competitive premiums with quite solid comprehensive features.
Now like I mentioned at the start of this video in comparison to the previous plan it might be 2 to 4
percent more expensive but they're still quite competitive. So let's take a 25 year old nonsmoker
male buying a 1 crore plan till the age of 65. A 1 crore plan would cost him about 10,000, a 2 crore
plan would cost him about 17,000 and a 3 crore would be about 25,000. Pretty good rates. The next profile for a slightly older individual, a 40 year old male buying it till 65. A 1 crore plan would cost him somewhere about 20,000, a 2 crore plan would be somewhere about 35,000 and a 3 crore is somewhere at about 52,000. So again not bad if you compare it to other insurers out there this is reasonable and quite competitive. So finally before we head towards the end of the video Sushant I want to ask you. You've
seen many term plans out there. What is your take on Max Life taking back their STEP plan and bringing in STPP? So do you think it's a step up or a step down? Definitely a step up I think because they've maintained some of the good features from STEP and they've brought in a host of new features as well. One thing I particularly liked was a couple of features specifically targeting the female audience. I thought that was quite interesting and thoughtful of them to do.
Additionally offering variants in terms of customization and so on. I thought that was comprehensive as well. The ROP variants of course maybe we're not the happiest with that but you can't be too happy.
Perfect. Thank you so much Sushant for joining us and folks you heard it from the expert himself. So STPP plan is really a good one in the market at the moment. So if you guys want to book a call with us to know more about STPP plan and if it's the right one for you,
then please book the call with us with the link in the description. I'll see you in the next one. Happy insurance hunting.