Okay, so let me ask you this, if someone told you that two term plans can give both, give
your money back and give you a flexibility, but cost very differently, would you know
how to choose?
Because today we are comparing two heavyweights, Axis Max Life's Smart Term Plan Plus and
Bajaj Alliance Life's eTouch 2.
And trust me, while they may look very similar on the surface, there are some serious differences
once you dig a little deeper.
Hello folks, I'm Shashank from Return Insurance and if you're confused about which term
plan is genuinely better for you, don't stress. Book a free call with our advisors and we'll help
you figure it out calmly and simply. No spam, no pushy sales. Link is in the description. And yes,
our services, they're totally free. Alright, let's jump straight into the comparison. First,
a quick background. Axis Maxlife is one of the most reliable insurers in the market today. Their
CSR is one of the best in the industry and they've got a solid Axis bank back in now and operationally
they've been getting stronger every year. Bajaj Alliance Life on the other hand brings a powerful
combination of Indian trust and global expertise. Its solvency ratio is over 5.1 times which is
insane stability and their claims settlement ratio over 99% and it is one of the highest in the
industry. So should I trust them with my money point of view? Both are solid, no issues. Now
coming to the plans. STPP is Axis Max Life's flagship term plan. It replaced their older
step plan. The beauty of STPP is flexibility. You can pick from seven different variants. But honestly, for most people, only two make real sense.
The regular cover and the smart cover Bajaj Alliance eTouch 2 meanwhile keeps it simpler It offers a standard life shield variant an accidental cover variant and a return of premium option But the biggest kicker It comes with an inbuilt zero cost exit option that genuinely a game changer
So let's do a proper head to head.
First, let's talk about coverage structure.
In STPP's regular cover, you get simple lump sum death payout, no fancy changes over time.
Just plain solid term insurance.
In E-Touch 2's base variant, it's the same.
Clean term insurance but with a twist.
If you've crossed a minimum number of years and hit 860, you can actually surrender the policy and get back all your premiums.
And if you choose longer terms with limited pay, you might even get 2x the premiums back.
This feature is called 2x special exit.
This 2x special exit is in both the plans.
Axis Max Life launched it first and then Bajaj and ICICI launched it as well.
However, IRDI has directed them that they cannot give back 2x the premium paid.
So with that direction, ICICI has already retracted the 2x benefit.
Axis Maxlife and Bajaj would do it in the second half of May tentatively.
Now, what about plan flexibility?
Axis Maxlife STPP gives you 7 variant options.
Apart from regular cover, there's smart cover, rebalancing cover,
ROP options, whole life covers and even income protection options.
It's designed for people who want slightly customized structures
based on liabilities like home loans, education expenses, etc.
Bajaj Alliance, on the other hand, keeps it simple.
The E-Touch 2 plan says, you want basic cover? Take it.
Want early exit options? Take it.
Want critical illness or family protection riders?
Here, add them.
It's super streamlined without making you feel lost
in a sea of complicated variants.
Now let touch on zero cost exit versus special exit value Balik eTouch 2 offers zero cost exit if you cross 60 and meet minimum policy term criteria of 35 years You can exit anytime after 70 and take your premiums back
STPP, however, offers special exit.
You can exit and take premiums back starting from the 30th policy year,
but not during the last 4 years of the policy term.
Also, you need minimum 40-year policy terms to get this benefit.
Slightly more restrictive compared to Balik's clean zero-cost feature.
Now let's talk about premiums because money matters, right?
At age 30, for a non-smoker and salaried male for 1 crore cover till the age of 65,
STPP plan costs about Rs. 11,960 and second year onwards Rs. 14,000.
E-Touch 2 costs around Rs. 12,500 and second year onwards Rs. 14,800.
Slightly cheaper for STPP but not by a huge margin.
As you increase the sum assured to 2 crore or 3 crore,
E-Touch 2 actually becomes more price efficient,
especially after you factor in the discounts that Bajaj offers.
5% for salaried profile, 5% if you're new to life insurance,
and another 6% for buying online.
With Axis Max Life, you get a chunky 15% discount for salaried individuals,
but it's only on first-year premiums.
So, price-wise, if you plan to hold the policy for a long time,
Bajaj might edge out slightly due to consistent value across the top.
Now, onto riders and add-ons.
Both plans offer critical illness riders, accidental death riders,
and waiver of premium riders.
But Bacharach now allows you to stack a critical illness rider that covers up to 60 illnesses
while Axis Maxlife covers up to 64 illnesses.
Also, Balik's new Family Protect rider is very interesting.
It provides a lifelong monthly income for your parents if something happens to you It emotional planning and it very niche but very nice to have as well Now claims experience Both have instant payout on claim information
Both pay up to Rs 2 lakh paid within one working day of claim registration
even before full verification happens.
This can really help families during emotional emergencies like funerals or immediate costs.
Now, let's talk solvency and complaints.
Bajaj solvency ratio is an eye-popping 5.1 times,
meaning it's financially one of the most secure insurers out there today.
Axis Maxlife solvency is good too but not as crazy high,
around 2x which is also the industry average.
Complaints ratio are low for both,
but Bajaj Edge is slightly better with 4.4 complaints per 10,000
compared to Axis at around 7 to 8.
Alright, final comparison takeaway,
if you're someone who wants maximum flexibility,
wants the cleanest early exit option and doesn't want to overthink variants,
Bajaj Alliance eTouch 2 is a super practical option.
But if you love customization like tailoring your plans based on liabilities,
want niche covers like smart cover with boosted coverage in early years,
waiver of premium on critical inners as well as want a salary discount upfront
in a good chunk, Axis Maxlife STPP gives you way more configuration power.
And again, if you're still thinking,
yaar I'm still confused, both sound too good, just book a free call with Ditto's advisors,
we'll explain your options based on your profile and help you pick the policy based on your life
situation not some generic online review link is in the description and yes it's
completely free all right folks that's it for today if you found this video
helpful drop a like and subscribe if you haven't already for more comparison and
reviews and I will see you in the next one until then have enjoy and something