Your surgery gets done in 3 hours, no overnight stay, no hospital bed and yet the bill is
50,000 rupees.
You say, alright I'll file a claim.
The insurer says, claim rejected, no 24 hour admission.
Now what?
That's where day care procedures come in.
And today we're going to simplify this essential but misunderstood benefit in health insurance.
Hey everyone, I'm Shashank from Ditto and in this episode of Health Insurance 101, we'll
explain what day care procedures are, which treatments qualify and what you should check
in your policy to avoid nasty surprises later.
And if you're unsure whether your plan covers these, you can always book a free call with
Ditto.
No jargon, no spam.
Just clear answers.
The link is in the description.
Now let's start with the basics.
Traditionally, insurance claims were allowed only if you were hospitalised for more than
24 hours.
But thanks to medical tech, many surgeries and treatments today are completed in just
a few hours.
That's where day care procedures come in.
These are treatments that would normally need hospitalisation but now can get done
in less than 24 hours due to modern techniques.
And yes, they are covered by most modern insurance plans.
Examples?
Cataract surgery, chemotherapy, dialysis, tonsil removal, hernia surgery, nearthroscopy
and so on.
Each insurer usually has a list of 100-600 plus such treatments.
Some plans now even cover any medically necessary day care procedures, not just those on the
list.
But note, it must be done in a hospital or surgical centre only and not just at a doctor's
clinic.
You'll need discharge surgeries and procedures notes to file a claim.
Day care vs OPD.
Now what's the difference between them?
If it's a short surgery under medical supervision in a hospital setup, it's called day care.
If it's just a consultation or a basic scan, it's OPD.
And OPD isn't usually covered unless you've taken as an add-on.
So why is day care covered a must-have?
Because modern healthcare is fast.
Cataracts, chemo, kidney stone removal, all of these can cost 50,000 rupees or more per
And you shouldn't lose a claim just because you didn't stay overnight.
So if you're buying insurance for seniors or anyone with chronic conditions, day care
covered is essential.
Here's what you should check in in your policy.
How many procedures are covered?
Is it fixed list or an open-ended clause?
Is cashless available for day care?
Is there any waiting period for specific procedures?
And final tip folks, never assume a treatment is day care or excluded.
Ask your doctor for written documentation and check with your insurer or PPA in advance.
And if you want help reading your policy or understanding your options, book a free call
with Ditto.
We'll make it easy.
In the next episode, we'll talk about domiciliary hospitalisation when treatment happens at
home but is still covered like regular hospitalisation.
If this episode helped you, share it with someone who's planning surgery.
Let's make India more insurance aware.
Happy insurance hunting.