Tata as a brand needs no introduction in India.
Known for its trust, legacy and customer first approach, the group has built credibility across sectors,
from automobiles to steel to telecom.
But what about insurance?
Is Tata AIG's health insurance actually worth your money in today's competitive market?
That is what we'll break down in this video.
Hello folks, I'm Shashank.
You're watching Ditto Insurance and in this video, we'll take a detailed look into how Tata AIG performs as an insurer,
how its plans stack in terms of features and value, and which of its five major products
may or may not make sense for your needs. And if you're new here, let me tell you that Ditto is an
insurance advisory platform and we stick by three things. Zero spam, no pressure to buy, and round
the clock free support. If you're looking to compare plans or purchase one, then Ditto's
experts can help you do exactly that by choosing the best health insurance and best term insurance
plans for you. All you need to do is book a free call with us with the link in the description.
Now, let's start with how Tata AIG performs as an insurer.
In terms of CSR, Tata AIG averages around 96% over the past 3 years.
That's quite impressive, better than ICICI Lombard and even close to HDFC Ergo.
When we look at the complaints volume, they stand at about 11 complaints per 10,000 claims.
Not the best, but still better than most public sector players.
Their ICR or incurred claim ratio is around 81%,
which means they're paying out a decent share of the premiums collected as claims.
The network hospital strength is solid as well, over 11,000 hospitals,
which is well within the expected range for a top insurer like Tata AIG.
Now coming to the actual plans, Tata AIG currently offers 5 main health insurance plans under its Medicare branding.
Let's break each one down one by one.
First is Medicare, which is their standard offering.
It a clean straightforward plan with decent coverage and minimal restrictions There are no room rent limits no disease sub no co clauses and pre and post are covered for 60 and 90 days and you get a restoration once a year although only after the first claim
and for the same illness, there's a 45-day waiting period.
The plan includes in-built consumables cover,
AYUSH and global cover for treatments diagnosed in India.
Bonus is 50% per year capped at 100%.
The health check-up is once every two claim-free years.
At a premium of Rs. 12,300 for a 30-year-old adult, it's reasonably priced.
Next is Medicare Lite and frankly, this one doesn't stand out.
It feels like a stripped-down version of the Medicare, made to compete with cheaper options.
While it does offer pre- and post-hospitalization coverage of 60 and 180 days
and includes hearing aid coverage and annual checkups, it comes with major drawbacks.
There's a copayment of 20% if you buy it after age 61
and a 30% copayment if treated outside Tata's preferred hospital network.
Restoration is limited to once per year and the no claim bonus drops after a claim.
Premium for a 30-year-old is Rs. 10,000 which is lower but the trade-offs in flexibility and post-claim benefits may not justify the saving.
Then comes Medicare Premium which is their most comprehensive retail plan.
This one is designed for people who want benefits beyond traditional hospitalization like maternity, OPD, dental and high-end diagnostics.
It removes room and restrictions and disease-wise sub-limits and offers restoration global cover, inbuilt consumables and vaccination benefits as well.
Maternity cover ranges from 50,000 to 1 lakh rupees depending on the sum insured and comes
with child specific benefits if a girl child is born.
OPD, dental and diagnostics are accessible after 2 years and scale up depending on your
coverage level.
It's clearly a high end plan and is priced accordingly.
For a 30 year old, the premium is 14,100 rupees which is on the higher side but justifiable
given the added features Before we head to the next plan let me remind you that Ditto services are totally free for you right from applications to claim support we are your insurance buddies book that free 30 minute call with the link in the description and start your stress insurance
journey now let's talk about elder care which is a basic plan designed for senior citizens between
the ages of 65 and 85 it offers some insured options from 5 to 25 lakhs but has several
limitations there's a mandatory copay of 20 percent sublimits on surgeries no domiciliary
coverage and no restoration benefit. Even the pre and post coverage is limited to 30 and 60 days
and while there is an option to waive off the copay by paying extra, the plan still feels
underwhelming. It's more of a fallback option for those who are struggling to find approval
for other plans. For a senior couple aged 62, the premium can go as high as Rs. 83,000 for basic
coverage. Lastly, there is Medicare Plus Super Top-Up, which is Tata's super top-up offer. It's
a solid plan with deductibles starting from 2 to 20 lakhs and some insured options from 3 lakh to
1 crore. No room rent limits, no co-payments and no sub-limits make it quite consumer friendly.
It includes inbuilt consumables, annual checkups and AYUSH. This plan is meant for people who
already have base insurance or are looking to build a layered cover affordably. It does its
job well without any unreasonable exclusions. Now, let's break down the premium numbers.
In Delhi, for a sum insured of 10 lakh rupees, a 30-year-old individual pays 12,300 for Medicare,
10,000 rupees for Medicare Lite and 14,100 for Medicare Premier. For a couple aged 30,
the costs are 19,700, 16,000 rupees and 22,000 respectively. A family of three with two 30-year-old
adults and a five-year-old child pays 23,500 for Medicare, 19,200 for Lite and 27,300 for Premier.
Now purely from a cost perspective the standard Medicare plan strikes a good balance between affordability and coverage Medicare Lite might appeal to budget buyers but its restrictive features weaken its long value
Medicare Premier is expensive but worthy if you truly need maternity, OPD, and other high-end benefits.
Eldercare should be looked at only if you have limited options elsewhere.
And the Super Top-Up plan is a good complement if you already have a base plan.
But even with all this, there's one important thing that you need to consider.
Tata AIG may win in trust and reliability as a brand and its plans are clean and well-priced.
But they don't push the envelope like other insurers in the market like HDFC Ergo,
Care Health, Niva Bupa and ICICI Lombard. Their offerings have better bonus structures,
better restoration terms and more innovative features through add-ons.
If you're looking for best class value, Tata may feel a little basic unless they upgrade
their plan variants and customization options.
So before you decide, here are 3 questions that you might need to ask yourself.
1.
How much do you value brand trust vs cutting edge benefits?
2.
Do you need high end features like maternity or OPD or are you just looking for solid basic
hospitalization?
And 3.
Are you okay with going for simpler plan with fewer frills or do you want every rupee of
premiums to pack in most possible benefits?
If you're still confused about which plan to go with, Tata, AIG or any other, don't worry.
Just book a free call with Ditto's expert insurance advisors.
We'll help you compare your options, explain all the fine print
and make sure you pick a plan that actually fits your needs and budget.
The link is in the description.
No spam, no pressure, just honest advice.
That's all for today, folks.
If this breakdown helped you, give this video a thumbs up
and subscribe to the channel for more honest reviews.
I'll see you in the next one.
Until then, happy insurance hunting.
you