Hi folks, welcome to Ditto Insurance.
This is one video that you should really not miss watching
because after watching this video,
you will know that you can claim reductions in your income tax
if you have a health or a term insurance.
So to explain each and every bit of the ATC and the ATD deductions,
I have with me the Senior Program Manager here at Ditto, Sushant.
Welcome Sushant.
Thanks Sushant.
Sushant, I think we are living in a time where we are being taxed even for different flavors of popcorn.
Though there have been a lot of memes floating around, you cannot ignore the fact that at the moment, we are being taxed the most in India.
And anywhere where we can save money on our ID returns, I think we should grab a chance.
So if the folks are watching this video have a health or term insurance, they do have the right to know that they can claim reductions on their IT interns.
So let's start the video without any delay. So what do you have for us?
I think we have a tax season around the corner. This is definitely a hot topic of discussion.
And not only that, I think with the fact that we're a country with dual tax schemes or dual tax regimes, it's obviously confusing for a few people.
firstly to understand how this even works and then to also get an idea on which one is more
suited for them. So just to probably give them a rough just a rough overview before we go into it
the old tax regime offers deductions as well but has higher tax slabs meaning the amount of tax
or the percentages of tax I need to pay they pay that are higher but they have deductions wherein
suppose my income for the year was 10 lakhs I can claim deductions for life insurance health insurance and various other things thereby bringing down my taxable income So that one aspect of it
which is the old regime. And the new regime doesn't offer any deductions whatsoever. And it
has lower slabs as well. So like I said, it really comes down to your specific profile and which one
would suit you better. But we'll of course today be discussing just the insurance specific aspects
of the reductions because obviously we're not you know CAs or CA certified sort of individuals here
so I think it's right it's best to stick to just the insurance part of it. Right so what do you
want to start with term or health? Let's do term first I think because that's a bit more simple and
straightforward. Okay. So any form of life insurance not just term insurance any form of life insurance
the premium that you pay can be claimed under section 80C of the Income Tax Act. Now 80C has
a limit of 1.5 lakhs per year. Now there's also a rule that came in that any policy purchased after
April 1st 2012, your premiums should not cross more than 10% of the sum insured for you to be
eligible for this. Now just to give you an example of what I mean by that, let's say if somebody has
a term insurance plan of 3 crore and his yearly premium is 50,000 rupees. This is well within 10%.
this rule comes in more for endowment plans or ULI plans the other forms of life insurance
wherein my sum insured itself is you know 10 lakhs and my premiums per year are one lakh change
because there's obviously investment and insurance combined into this right but here what essentially
would happen is my premium has crossed 10 percent of the sum insured 10 lakh plan the premium itself
1 lakhs um so that obviously wouldn be possible for me to claim under ATC it a very rare edge case situation but no harm in sort of just highlighting it Pure term insurance pure life insurance nothing to worry about It under if it within 1 lakhs
you can claim it here.
That's what it looks like, yeah.
All right, Sushant.
Now let's take a look at health insurance deductions.
Yes, so I think this has a separate section
just for itself.
It starts with foresee 25,000 as the limit.
This is section 80D.
So there's 25,000 as a limit if you're buying health insurance for yourself and your family.
Now, if you're buying health insurance for your parents as well, you have a separate 25,000 limit that you can claim for them.
It gets even better if your parents are above the age of 60.
If your parents are senior citizens, considering the fact that their premiums also shoot up,
the insurance companies and actually the government more than that has sort of acknowledged that since the premium you're paying is higher, the limit should be higher as well.
So now it's 25,000 for you and your family.
And if your parents are senior citizens, it's 50,000, not 25.
So you have a sum total of 75,000 that you can claim here.
Now, taking it one step further as well, if you yourself and your parents are senior citizens,
if an individual is, let's say, 60 and his parents are 80, mid-80s or so,
the limit goes up to 1 lakh now, considering that for both individuals combined,
the premiums would be quite exorbitant.
So they have given some flexibility and they've been considered with the age as well.
I think that that's one of the most important ones here.
Right, because unlike life insurance, health insurance premiums keep going up with age.
And they don't want a customer to feel that burden, but especially beyond 60, there's a chance you're not even working, you're not earning, but you're paying these high premiums.
So there should be some form of benefit that you're getting.
Additionally under ATD there another section called ATDD So this is for people with special disabilities So for is taking care of his family members who have special disabilities there a separate section
where you can claim expenses that you're sort of incurring to, you know, for their livelihood.
It's about 75,000 for normal disabilities and 1.25 lakhs for special disabilities.
So it's a separate section that they have to kind of take care of this as well.
All right, Shashank. Now, do our audience need to keep anything else in their mind?
Yes, there's a couple of pointers I would like to highlight.
One, always make your payments through digital modes, meaning a UPI, a debit or credit card or any sort of online payment.
You can't pay in cash is my point, because for those you won't be able to claim any deductions.
You have to show proof of payment.
This actually might be possible maybe through some offline agents, but most online channels where you purchase insurance, you won't have to worry about this.
Secondly, please make sure you have all your documentation in place.
so in order to actually claim these tax benefits
your CA will ask you to submit the premium receipts
that come with your insurance policy
the separate receipt that the insurance companies will share with you
which is used for tax purposes
it's in the correct format and everything
you just need to make sure you have that document ready
I think that's about it
there's really not much else to be mindful of
Alright Sushant, thank you so much for this
quick and short
I think explainer on how people can save on taxes
if they have health and term insurance
So folks, if you don't have a health or term insurance yet, then there is no better time than buying it now.
So book your free consultation with Ditto with the link in the description.
And if you already have a health and term insurance and if you have doubts regarding the taxes then,
then you can comment in the comments box and we will get back to you.
Or again, you can book a call with us and we will clarify it for you.
I'll see you guys in the next one.
Happy insurance hunting.