You've heard of term plans, you've heard of return of premium plans, but what if I told
you there's a version where you get all your money back and you don't have to pay extra
for it?
Yes, that's the promise of a zero-cost term plan.
Sounds too good to be true, right?
Let's break it down.
Hi folks, I'm Shashank and you're watching Ditto Insurance.
And if you've been stuck trying to decide between regular term plan, return of premium
plans or these new zero-cost ones, the video is just for you.
If you're still confused after this, book a free call with our advisors.
The link is in the description.
No spam, no upselling, just clear personalized advice.
What is zero-cost term plan?
At its core, a zero-cost term plan is just a regular term insurance policy,
but with one extra feature.
And what is that?
You get an optional exit window.
Okay, now what does that mean?
This means at a certain point in the future,
say after 25 years or when you turn 60,
you can exit the policy and get your base premiums refunded.
No bonus, no interest, just the premiums you paid,
minus taxes and rider charges.
That's it.
If you don't exit, it functions exactly like a regular term plan.
It gives you the life cover till the end.
No refund at maturity though.
So essentially, zero cost is equal to regular term plan,
plus exit option, plus refund on exit.
It's called zero cost because if you exit and get back your premiums,
your net cost becomes close to zero.
Assuming of course, there's no death claim before that.
Now, let's look at how this works.
Say you're 30.
You buy a 40-year term plan with 1 crore cover.
You pay 20,000 rupees a year as premium.
At 55 age, you paid for 25 years.
Your kids are working, loans are done, you don't need life cover anymore.
You're sorted.
So, you decide to exit the term plan.
And now the insurer refunds 5 lakh rupees, roughly the base premium you paid.
The life cover stops but you also stop paying Simple right Now you might be wondering Shashank what is the catch here And that where we come in Let go deeper See you actually don get a full refund
The amount refunded doesn't include GST, which is around 18%,
and it doesn't include rider costs, and doesn't include any growth or interest.
So, if you're hoping for a bonus, there isn't one.
Also, inflation hits real hard.
A 10 lakh refund after 25 years might only be worth 3-4 lakh in today's money or even lesser.
So while you do get your money back, it doesn't feel like much when you factor in the concept of time.
But compared to return of premium plans, this is still way better because
ROP plans charge 70-100% higher premiums for that refund.
Zero cost term plans, they usually have similar pricing to normal term plans
as long as you don't stretch your policy unnecessarily.
Now here's something most people miss.
To qualify for the refund, you sometimes need to take a longer policy term.
Now, let's say you only need life cover till 65, which is also what we recommend at Ditto.
But the insurer says you can only exit and get a refund if your policy goes till 75 or 80 years.
Now, you're buying 10 to 15 extra years of cover you don't actually need just to get that refund,
which means you pay more premiums, you're overinsured,
and you take on risk of staying in longer than necessary.
So yes, zero cost is better than ROP, but it still needs smart planning.
And by the way, if you want help figuring out what term duration actually suits your life goals,
not what the insurer says you should pick, book a free call with Ditto.
The link is in the description.
Now, a question we get asked all the time.
Why would insurers even offer this feature?
Won't it be a loss for them?
Well, the answer is it works in their favor too.
I'll tell you how.
For starters, it makes term plans more attractive.
The number one reason people hesitate to buy term insurance is because what if I survive and get nothing back This refund feature eases that concern More sales for them It also improves policy persistency and when you know you get a refund someday
you're more likely to keep paying premiums year after year
and that's great for the insurer.
And here's the biggest one.
Risk reduction.
If you exit the plan after 25-30 years,
you're doing it before the riskiest phase
that is 860 and beyond when most death claims happen.
So the insurer refunds your premium
and quietly walks away from the high risk years.
For them, it's a good trade.
For you, it's a psychological win.
Okay, now let's compare this with the return of premium plans.
Everyone keeps asking us to compare them.
Now, ROP plans charge nearly double the premiums
and you have no exit flexibility.
And you only get your money back if you survive the full term.
No chance to walk away earlier.
Zero cost term plans, on the other hand, give you an out.
You can exit early, take a refund and be done.
Both return only base premiums.
No interest, no growth.
but at least zero cost doesn't overcharge you from day one.
Now, who should consider a zero cost term plan?
Listen to this because this is important.
It works best for young earners, say people in their 20s and early 30s,
people expecting to retire early or don't want to commit till age 80,
those who don't like the idea of losing money if they survive,
and people with evolving financial goals and say you're unsure if you'll need cover beyond 60.
Now this, it gives you flexibility.
And what does Ditto recommend?
We actually like zero-cost term plans not because they're revolutionary, but because they strike a good balance.
Most comprehensive term plans today already include this exit option as a built-in feature.
You're not even paying extra for it.
But here's the catch.
Don't stretch your policy artificially just to get the refund.
If your insurance need ends at 65, don't buy a plan till 85 just to be eligible for that exit.
That defeats the whole purpose.
And finally when you reach that exit window say after 25 years you don have to exit Let say you 55 kids are grown loans are cleared but you still want the cover just in case Guess what Your premiums they stay the same It was fixed years ago That
the beauty of term plan. So even if the 1 crore summer short has lost value due to inflation,
it's still a solid cover and you've already paid most of your premiums. At this point,
exiting might not be worth it and that's okay too. You have the choice. And by the way,
if you want to check whether your current plan has this exit option or whether switching to a
zero-cost plan makes sense for your age and goals, book a free call with Ditto. It's free,
it's spam-free, and it could save you lakhs of rupees. You will find the link in the description.
Before we wrap up, here's a quick list of insurers offering zero-cost or smart exit features.
HTC Life's Click2Protect Super, Elite Plus, and Ultimate. ICICI Prudential iProtect Smart and
Super. Axis MaxLife STPP, that is Smart Term Plan Plus. Bajaj Alliance, eTouch2, and iSecure2.
Just make sure to check the exit window, eligibility conditions, and refund rules in each case.
These differ across insurers.
Oh, and one last thing,
you might have heard about some plans offering 2x refund at the exit.
Yeah, that existed, but very briefly.
ICICI, Bajaj and AccessMax Life were offering double the premiums
you paid for if you opted for limited pay.
But IRDI stepped in and said, hold up,
you can't refund more than 100% in a term plan.
So these plans are now being rolled back for some new buyers.
But if you already bought it, don't worry, your benefits are still valid.
That's the full picture, folks.
Zero cost term plans aren't magic, but they're a smart middle path.
You get solid cover, flexibility to walk away midway,
and none of the overcharging that comes with return of premium.
This don't fall for the marketing line blindly.
Understand how the exit works, when it works,
and whether it makes sense for you to actually use it.
And if you need help figuring this all out, you know where to go.
Book a call with Ditto. Free advice, real advice.
The link is in the description.
Thanks for watching folks. I'll see you in the next one.
Until then, happy challenge hunting!