You might be planning a baby or maybe just thinking about it. Either way, maternity costs in 2025 are no joke.
In cities like Mumbai, Delhi, Pune, even Ahmedabad, the delivery itself can just cost you around 25,000 rupees to 1.25 lakh rupees.
And that's for a normal or C-sectional delivery. Add in prenatal checkups, scans, medications, NICU bills, vaccinations and the numbers balloons up really fast.
So naturally, the next question becomes, can insurance help with this?
Short answer, yes. Long answer, it depends.
Maternity insurance is a tricky space, full of fine print, waiting periods,
sublimits, expensive riders and hidden conditions as well.
So in this video, we'll break it all down.
The best maternity insurance plans for 2025 based on real numbers,
real benefits and real trade-offs.
We'll cover waiting periods, coverage limits, advanced features like IVF or surrogacy,
newborn coverage and even actual premium coats.
And just like our ultimate term guide, there are chapters in the description.
Skip to the plan you want, come back later or just stick around and learn it all.
And if at any point you feel overwhelmed, we're here.
Book a free call with ditto, no spam, no pressure, just honest insurance guidance.
The link is in the description.
Alright, let's dive in.
Now, before we head to the plans, let me give you a quick reality check.
A maternity policy isn't like a regular health insurance because it's built around a high
probability short-term event, which means insurers protect themselves through five common
restrictions.
Number one, waiting periods ranging from nine months to four years.
So if you're already pregnant or planning next year, many plans may not be useful right now.
Number two, sublimits.
Fixed caps on maternity claims like 40,000 or 60,000 rupees.
If your bill is one lakh, you pay the rest by yourself.
Third, higher premiums.
Plans with maternity bundled in can be twice as expensive.
Fourth, dual coverage rule.
Many policies require both spouses to be insured under the same plan.
And finally, no refund clause.
If maternity is bundled into your base plan you continue paying that high premium even after you done with kids That why our advice is always check your corporate cover first Corporate health policies often have no waiting periods generous maternity limit and built newborn cover And they typically paid by your employer
But if you don't have a company plan or need a personal policy, here are the best options
available today. Starting with Aditya Birla ActiveFit, preferred with inbuilt maternity.
This plan offers well-rounded coverage with fitness-linked rewards. Maternity kicks in
after a three-year wait.
Rs. 40,000 for normal delivery,
Rs. 60,000 for C-sectional.
Covers two deliveries or two terminations
or one of each.
Newborn expenses covered for 90 days
plus vaccinations till age 2.
It even includes stem cell storage costs
but within the maternity limit.
Also, it's only applicable
if both spouses are covered under the same plan.
It offers health returns
and a good health discount
for those with low risk profiles.
Also, there is no rent cap
for someone short above Rs. 5,000,000
and full restoration across illnesses.
Talking about premiums for a couple age 25, it'll come around 16,249 and for age 30, 70,680 rupees.
So it's great for people who are health conscious and want long-term value out of their plan and not just maternity.
Alright, moving ahead to the next plan.
Neva Bupa Aspire Titanium Plus with maternity inbuilt.
Possibly the most feature-loaded maternity policy in the market.
Why? Because waiting period is just 9 months.
It covers IVF, surrogacy, infertility treatments and even adoption-related costs.
Delivery plus newborn care plus vaccinations all included.
The miracle benefit accumulates over time if unused.
There is no copay, no room rent limits, no disease-wise sublimits as well.
It works for individuals and you don't need both spouses on this plan.
Add-ons like Fast Forward gives you a 3-year coverage pool up front.
Future Ready lets you carry forward waiting periods for a future spouse.
Now, talking about premiums for a couple aged 25, it comes around Rs 16,197
Rs. and for a couple aged around 30, it comes around the same, Rs. 16,680. If you're early
in your planning journey and want maximum flexibility, this plan might be for you. Alright,
moving ahead we have ICICI Lombard Elevate with maternity as an add Now this one is a serious business but it comes at a price Maternity is available as a paid add not built It covers three deliveries terminations and postnatal care
Limit is 10% of annual sum insured and capped at 1 lakh rupees.
There is a two-year waiting period which can be reduced to one via add-on again.
It includes vaccination and ICU and newborn hospitalization as well.
Also, covers surrogacy and oocyte donor costs up to 5 lakh rupees.
It also has a good wellness discount, bariatric surgery and other advanced add-ons as well.
Talking about premiums, for a couple age 25, it can come up to 63,500 rupees and for a couple age 30, around 64,000 rupees.
Now, if you're looking for a maternity plan that doubles as a high-end family health policy, ICICI Elevate is excellent but quite expensive.
Alright, moving ahead, we have Star Health's Superstar Policy with maternity as an add-on.
This is one of the most modular and flexible maternity add-ons in the market.
Now, there are three configurations.
Option A, 50,000 to 1 lakh rupees per delivery after 24 months.
Option B, 30,000 rupees per delivery after 12 months.
Or option C, IVF or ART support up to 4 lakh rupees based on some insurance.
Now, newborn cover kicks in from day one.
It also includes women care add-on that covers congenital conditions as well.
The future shield add-on lets your spouse inherit waiting period credits post-marriage.
Also, there is a freeze your age feature where you can lock in your premiums until age 56.
Now, the premiums vary with the configurations.
For option A, it is between 29,000 to 30,000.
For option B, it is between 33,000 to 35,000.
And for option C, it is 1.12 lakh plus.
So, who should go in for this?
It's best suited for those who want modular control or are specifically planning for ART treatments.
Now, we have Tata AIG Medicare Premier with inbuilt maternity benefit.
This is a high credibility plan with inbuilt maternity, designed for simplicity.
Waiting period is 4 years and coverage is Rs 50,000 to 1 lakh depending on some insured
and extra 10 to 20 rupees if it a girl child It includes vaccination costs newborn delivery complications and there is no copay no room rent gap and excellent complaint ratio And there are no much complaints
Offers global cover for plant treatments, dental, physio, and more.
Premiums for a couple age 25, around 23,500.
A couple age 30, 25,500.
It's a strong, reliable plan if you're already midway through your waiting period
or want a maternity-inclusive plan that doesn't require mental gymnastics.
Now, there are also other plans worth mentioning.
HDFC Ergo Optima Secure with Parenthood add-on.
So it covers two deliveries or termination, has IVF support, pre and postnatal cover, but no newborn care here.
Manipal Signa Sarva Uttam with the add-on covers up to 5 lakh rupees for maternity, vaccination and newborn care.
But the waiting period is for 3 years.
There's also Carejoy today which has inbuilt maternity and newborn birth defect cover, but high premiums and low sum insured and weaker core features.
Now, how to choose the right plan?
Here's the truth, there is no single plan that wins on every metric.
If you want comprehensive reproductive benefits like IVF surrogacy adoption,
go with Niva Bupa Aspire Titanium Plus.
If you need fast entry and don't want both spouses on policy, again, Niva Bupa stands out.
If your timeline is flexible and you're already insured, consider Aditya Birla Active Fit.
If you want a well-rounded, globally portable plan with in-built maternity,
Tata AIG Medicare Premier gets your bet.
If you're willing to pay for maximum flexibility and extras,
ICICI Elevate or Star Health Superstar is a good one for you.
Now, what's the conclusion?
Don't get maternity insurance just because you're supposed to.
Get it because the timing, features, and trade-offs actually work for you.
If you're 2-3 years away from planning a child, now may be the time to buy.
If you're already pregnant, corporate cover may be your best shot.
And if you're lost between the plan, brochures, riders, and jargon, Ditto is here for you.
Book a free one-on-one call with a Ditto advisor today,
and we'll walk you through your options, compare plans with you,
and help you choose something that fits your life.
No spam, no sales pleasure, just pure clarity.
That's it from our side.
I'm Shashank, and you're watching Ditto Insurance.
if this helped you share it with a friend who's thinking about starting a family and I'll see you
in the next one with fewer doubts and more confidence. Until then, happy insurance hunting.