I don't need to tell you the thrill of travelling.
Whether you visit in the scenic beaches of Thailand or exploring through aesthetic city
streets of Italy.
There is nothing quite like the excitement of packing your bags and hopping onto the
very next flight.
But let's be here.
Travel can also come with its own set of untradictable plot twists.
Lost luggage, missed flights or a sudden illness can turn your dream vacation into a stressful
mess.
And while we are dead or don't specifically deal with travel insurance because we focus
primarily on health and term insurance only.
We couldn't resist making this video to help our wanderlust audience.
After all ensuring your covered, wherever life takes you is what we are all about.
So folks if you need help with your health or term insurance then book a free chat with
our expert advisors.
Today and get personalized advice.
Now let's start with today's topic.
Travel insurance.
At its core travel insurance is your financial safety net wherever you are travelling abroad.
It covers everything from emergency medical treatment to dental procedures and even steps in if
you face accidents during your journey.
But that's not all.
It also has your back if you need to cancel your trip in the end or if you lose your luggage
or even if your home gets burglarized when you are away.
Now when it comes to types of travel insurance you've got two main options.
First there's single trip insurance perfect for those one of adventures lasting up to
180 days.
Then we have multi trip insurance which is ideal for frequent travelers who make multiple
trips within a year.
Typically covering 30 to 60 days per trip.
Now let's talk about why travel insurance is great.
Well it's comprehensive covering a wide range of travel risks and it won't break the
bank compared to international medical insurance which will come to in a later stage.
Plus getting it is as easy as ordering your morning coffee.
The application process is super simple but like everything else it does have its limitations.
It's primarily designed for shorter stays so if you're planning to be abroad for an extended
period then you might want to think twice.
Also it mainly covers emergency medical treatment so don't count on it for routine checkups and
here's a big one.
If you have any PDs that is pre-existing medical conditions you might find yourself in a tight
spot as these are often excluded.
Now let's look at some of the best travel insurance options available in India.
First up is HTFC Ergo which gives you access to over 1 lakh cashless hospital worldwide.
They've got you covered for everything from medical emergencies to COVID-19 related
incidents.
Their policy is incredibly flexible, accommodating everyone from business travelers to holiday
makers with family coverage options as well.
The plan includes emergency medical evacuation, repatriation of remains, accidental death
and disability coverage and financial assistance if you get robbed.
What's great is that they cover people from 6 months to 70 years old and you can choose
between single trips or annual multitript plans.
Next up, Tata AIG's Travel Guard Plus is another excellent option offering coverage from
$50,000 up to $1 million.
They're particularly great with instant claim settlements and have special provisions
for senior citizens.
Their coverage extends to emergency medical evacuation, repatriation costs and they offer
some fantastic discounts for families.
One standout feature is their geographical flexibility.
That is you can choose worldwide coverage or exclude specific regions based on your needs.
Plus they provide loyalty benefits for returning customers making it a great choice for frequent
travelers.
Next up, Bajaj Alihan's individual travel insurance plan matches these impressive coverage
limits ranging from $50,000 again up to $1 million.
They offer cashless hospitalization and their worldwide network of hospitals, emergency medical
evacuation and repatriation of remains.
What sets them apart is their specialized options for senior citizens and their comprehensive
family coverage plan.
They also provide flexibility in selecting geographical coverage allowing you to customize
the plan based on your destination just like Tata AIG.
Next up, ICICI Lombards International Travel Insurance really stands out with its
age range.
It covers people from 3 months to 85 years.
Beyond the standard coverage, they offer unique benefits like compassionate visits for family
members during hospitalization and coverage for political risk and catastrophic evacuations.
Their daily hospitalization allowance aids extra financial security and they provide value
added services for dependence back home.
Plus there is no medical test required for policy issues making it incredibly convenient.
Now, let's switch gears and talk about medical insurance with international coverage.
This is the heavy hitter of the international insurance options.
Unlike travel insurance, this type of coverage is designed for both emergency and planned
medical procedures abroad.
It's perfect for those who might need extensive medical care while travelling or living overseas.
The advantages are very significant.
You get comprehensive medical coverage for both emergency and planned treatment, metadetic
coverage in some plans and many policies cover PEDs after a waiting period.
Plus, you can customize these plans with add-ons and wellness programs as well.
However, there are some drawbacks to consider.
The premiums are significantly higher than standard travel insurance and you might face deductibles
and copayments before your coverage kicks in.
Some plans also exclude high cost countries like the US and Canada and their generally only
available to resident Indians.
Let's dive deeper into the medical insurance plans with international coverage options.
First up, HCFC Optima Secure Global Plus is a powerhouse offering base coverage of
1-2-2 crores with no copayment or room and interstictions.
What's impressive is their benefit structure.
You get a 50% increase up to 100% irrespective of claims with no clawback.
They offer both cashless and reimbursement options with a small, ten-kid deductible
for international claims.
The plan includes comprehensive pre- and post-hospitalization coverage for 60 and 180 days respectively
and even covers consumables both in India and globally.
Next up, Care Advantage Plus with Global Cover.
It's another strong contender offering coverage from 25 lakhs all the way up to 6 crores.
They provide various innovative add-ons like annual health checkups, air ambulance
service and their unique care shield feature.
This plan increases your base cover as per the CPI index and covers consumables as well.
Their no-clim bonus super feature can increase your bonus by an extra 50% up to 100% of
the base cover.
Plus, they offer OPT coverage with specific consultation limits.
Next up, Niva Boopa Health Premium Platinum stands out with its unique combination of
health and travel benefits.
It offers coverage up to 2 crores and includes in-built travel insurance coverage for things
like loss passports and trip cancellations.
They even cover metanity expenses up to 2 lakhs globally except in US and Canada.
Their enhanced geographical scope add-ons extend coverage to the US and Canada making it
truly comprehensive.
Next up, the Niva Boopa Aspire with BODELESS add-on is particularly interesting.
Offering coverage from 3 lakhs all the way up to 1 crore.
It features innovative benefits like lock the clock premium feature and future-ready add-on
for adding future spouses.
Their boost-up plus benefit carries forward unutilized cover up to 10 times the base sum
in short.
And last on the list, Aditya Billa at T1 VIP Plus.
It offers extensive coverage from 50 lakhs to 6 crores with their super-credit feature
providing additional coverage up to 4 crores.
They include comprehensive travel insurance benefits and offer both emergency and plant
treatment coverage worldwide.
Their plan stands out with features like claim protect for consumables and super reload
for unlimited restoration.
Now let me share some real-world examples to help you understand better if you should
get a travel insurance or a medical insurance.
Take Asshama for example a 26 year old entrepreneur who frequently travels to UK, Australia and
New Zealand for business, which stable finances and frequent short trips she's perfect for
an international medical insurance plan.
Then there's Anita.
A 35 year old ID professional planning a family Christmas trip abroad.
Since it's a one time holiday trip, travel insurance would be ideal for her and her family.
Consider Sino, a 30 year old starting her fabric business.
Getting to visit Bangladesh for a month long training.
With unstable finances, travel insurance makes more sense for a 30 day stir.
And finally we have Hina, a 40 year old planning knee replacement surgery in the UK giving
her stable finances in the nature of her medical treatment.
Medical insurance with medical international coverage would be her best bet.
Now the question is when to choose which type of insurance.
You see travel insurance is essentially your short term safety net focusing primarily on
emergency situations and travel related issues.
It's designed for those quick business trips or family vacations offering protection against
unexpected medical emergency strip cancellation, laws, baggage and other unrelated mishaps.
Medical insurance with international coverage on the other hand is your comprehensive
health protection abroad.
It's like having your regular health insurance but with a global reach.
The key difference lies in the depth of coverage while travel insurance might cover that
emergency appendectomy.
International medical insurance would cover everything from routine checkups to plant surgeries
and even ongoing treatments for chronic conditions.
Think of it this way.
Travel insurance is like carrying a first aid kit for your journey.
Essential for immediate emergencies but limited in scope.
International medical insurance is more like having your entire health care system in your
pocket ready to use wherever you are in the world.
The cause difference reflects this disparity in coverage.
Travel insurance is typically more affordable because it's designed for short term emergency
only coverage.
International medical insurance commands higher premiums but provides the peace of mind
of knowing you're covered for any health related situation, plant or unplanned.
As we wrap up folks let's remember that choosing between travel insurance and medical
insurance with an international coverage isn't just about cost.
It's about understanding your specific needs and circumstances.
Consider your travel frequency the nature of your trips and your health conditions and
also your budget.
For frequent travelers or those planning extended stays abroad.
Medical insurance might be worth the higher premiums.
For occasional travelers or those on short trips travel insurance might be more practical
choice.
Remember to review the specific benefits, exclusions and claim procedures of any policies
you're considering.
Pay attention to geographical inflation, coverage caps and any waiting periods that might
apply.
An important note folks at Ditto we want to be completely transparent with you.
Our advisory services are primarily limited to health insurance coverage with an India
and term life insurance.
While we've provided this comprehensive overview of travel insurance options, we don't
currently facilitate travel insurance purchases throughout the platform.
Additionally when it comes to health insurance policies with international coverage we want
to be upfront about the fact that we have limited experience with the claim processes.
Since we haven't processed many cases in this area we can't provide detailed insight
into how smoothly these claims work in practice.
The work of insurance can be complex but making an informed decision about your coverage
can save you from significant stress and financial burden.
Take your time.
Evaluate your options carefully and choose the coverage that best fits your specific
situation and needs.
And if you need us to do the heavy lifting you know where to find us.
Thanks for watching folks.
Happy insurance hunting and safe travels.