You probably have a health insurance policy or maybe your company gave you one.
But if I asked you, what's your room rent limit or do you have a copay clause,
would you be able to answer? Now that's the problem.
Most of us have health insurance on paper, but when it's actually time to use it,
we have no idea how it works. And that can cost you a lot,
emotionally, financially, and even medically, which is why we made this video.
This is your ultimate health insurance guide.
We're going to cover everything from the basics like what health insurance is and why it matters
to the complex stuff like exclusions, restoration benefits, waiting periods, top-ups, super top-ups
and even how to file a claim when you're under pressure.
And yes, this will be quite a long video but we've added chapters in the description
so you can skip to any section you want.
Or better, watch it all in one go and walk away knowing exactly how to choose,
use and get the most out of your health insurance.
And if you still feel lost after this, just book a free call with Ditto's advisors.
We will not spam you. We will not pressurize you.
Just solid advice will be given to you.
The link is in the description.
Alright, let's get into it.
So, what is health insurance and why does everyone say it's so important?
It's basically a deal between you and an insurance company.
You pay them a premium every year and they agree to cover your medical expenses
like hospital stays, surgeries, daycare procedures and more
as per the terms of the policy.
It's meant to prevent you from draining your savings
during a health emergency.
Because let's face it,
medical costs today are insane.
Even a simple surgery can cost
2 to 3 lakh rupees in a good hospital.
A few days in the ICU can burn through
5-6 lakh rupees just like that.
Now, without insurance,
it's a financial disaster waiting to happen.
It also saves you tax under Section 80D
if you're on the old tax regime.
So yes, it's not just protection,
it's smart financial planning.
Now, let's bust some common myths we hear literally every day.
I'm young and healthy, I don't need insurance.
Wrong Accidents don ask for your age and lifestyle illnesses are hitting people in their 20s now Buy young get lower premiums and clear your waiting periods early My office already gives me insurance
Sure, but what happens when you switch jobs or retire?
That coverage ends.
You need a personal plan as your backup.
Next one. Insurance covers everything, right?
Nope. Every policy has limits.
Room rent caps, co-pays, waiting periods, exclusions.
That's why people get shocked during claims.
You have to know your policy.
Now, let's talk about types of health insurance.
Which one should you even get?
There's individual insurance where you get the full cover to yourself.
This is good if you're single or have specific medical needs.
Then there's family floater plans.
The entire family shares one sum insured.
Cheaper, yes, but if one person claims a lot, there's less left for the rest.
Next, senior citizen plans.
Folks over 60 usually come with copays and tougher underwriting,
but they cater to age-related issues.
Next up, super top-up plans.
This is a secret hack.
You pay for small hospital bills out of pocket or use a base policy,
but once the bill crosses say 3 lakh rupees, the top-up kicks in.
You can get a 20 lakh rupee cover extra at a super low cost.
Also, there is corporate plans from your employer and group plans
from alumni networks, banks, etc.
But these are rarely enough by themselves.
Now, let's talk features.
These are what make or break your claim experience.
Copay.
You'll have to pay a percentage of every bill.
It's usually forced on senior citizen plans.
If you can avoid it, please do.
Room rent limit.
Now, this one's nasty.
If your room rent is capped at Rs. 5000 per day,
but you take a Rs. 8000 per day room,
the insurer might reduce your entire claim,
not just the rent part.
Sublimits on diseases.
Like cataract cap at Rs. 30k.
If the surgery costs Rs. 50,000,
you pay the difference. Again, not an ideal situation.
Pre and post hospitalization. This covers tests and medicines done 60 days before and 180 days after admission.
Different for different policies and this is a must have The more the number of days the better Next daycare procedures Not all surgeries need 24 hours now Good policies cover 500 plus procedures of these types Restoration If you use your cover this feature refills it
Crucial if multiple people are covered
or if you're dealing with back-to-back hospitalization.
Next is no claim bonus.
You get a bonus for every claim free year.
Some plans give 50% more cover per year,
but some also reduce the bonus if you make a claim.
So, check that.
Next up, maternity cover.
Comes with long waiting periods,
usually two to four years.
only opt for it if you're planning a family soon. OPD and health checkups. They sound nice but are
often not worth with high premiums. Use them only if you really need them. Next up, we have
waiting periods. All these features that we just narrated, we have made an in-depth video explaining
each one of these benefits. I will link them in the description below. This is a part of Health
101 series that we've done. It's a playlist. Again, I'll link it in the description for you to see.
Alright, now moving on to waiting periods.
Every policy has them.
And there are different kinds of waiting periods.
The usual 30 days for general hospitalization except accidents,
2-4 years for pre-existing diseases,
2 years for specific surgeries like hernia, joint replacement, cataract,
2-4 years for maternity and newborn coverage.
Now, these are non-negotiable, so start early and let the clock run.
Because when you really need the cover, you want zero waiting periods left.
But there's also a way to reduce waiting periods.
We will tell you how a little later.
Now let's talk premiums and why do they keep changing?
The reason is because you move into higher age bands.
Because medical inflation goes up.
Because insurers revise prices.
And yes, your city matters too.
India uses zonal pricing.
So Mumbai and Delhi pay more than smaller towns.
If you move cities, tell your insurer.
Otherwise, they might cut claims later.
Alright, now how much cover is enough?
For individual at least 10-15 lakh rupees if you're in a metro, for families a floater
plan with 15-25 lakh rupees.
If you want solid peace of mind add 50 lakh top up for a few hundred bucks extra Don under insure once you fall sick or claim once getting more cover later becomes really hard because now the insurer sees you as a high risk Alright how long should you take health insurance for Now plans come for 1 2 3 years Longer term ones often have higher
discounts. Whatever you choose, keep renewing on time. Even a one-day gap can reset all your
waiting periods and no claim bonuses. Okay, now let's talk about the claims experience.
For planned surgeries, inform your insurer 48-72 hours in advance.
Fill out a pre-auth form at the hospital.
If it's approved, you get cashless treatment.
For emergencies, inform within 24 hours.
If you're in a network hospital, cashless works.
If not, you pay first and claim reimbursement later.
Remember, keep all the bills, discharge summary, prescriptions, scans, doctor notes.
Because missing paper might equal missing money.
Claims get rejected too and here's why.
You either didn't disclose a pre-existing condition when buying the policy
or maybe you claimed during a waiting period or let's say you chose a hospital room above your
policy's limit or maybe you submitted in company documentation or you forgot to renew your policy
i know it sucks but most rejections happen due to lack of awareness not fraud i have some final
thoughts these are some mistakes to avoid don't hide your medical history please declare everything
don't buy the cheapest plan just to save 500 rupees also don't skip reading about sub limits
and room rent limits. Don't rely only on your office plan. Don't forget to check the
insurers claim track record and most importantly don't wait for health care to buy insurance.
Folks are you still confused? That's okay. Health insurance is not something you learn in a single
day. That's exactly why we started Ditto. Book a free call with our advisors. We'll explain your
policy, show you the best options, compare plans and even assist with claims if needed. No spam,
No pressure, just for clarity.
The link's in the description.
Folks, if this video helped you, hit like, share it with someone who's been putting off
this decision and subscribe to the channel for more honest insurance content.
This was your ultimate health insurance guide.
I am Shashank and now you actually know how to use your policy when it matters.
I'll see you in the next one.
Until then, happy insurance hunting.