Hello everyone. So I'm sure the one pager you're seeing on your screens, you would have received it by now.
This has been sent to all YPL branches. Let's make most of this one pager.
It talks about something very powerful. It talks about the immense trust that our customers have in the participating fund of Max Life Insurance.
And it is a matter of pride for all of us that amongst all private life insurance companies,
we have one of the highest and the largest power funds AOM, which stands tall at 67,722 crores, which is a big, big number.
And while we are talking, while we are seeing this video, it is growing with every passing minute.
We have 21 lakh policyholders who will be getting benefited, will be getting bonus in this particular financial year.
That's not it. Our power fund is growing at 22% year on year from last 10 years. That's also so amazing to know.
And this time we have declared our ever highest bonus, which is 1,826 crores rupees.
All this is mentioned in this one pager that's there on your screen. Let's use this one pager.
You are cool as, you know, let's go and educate all our sellers. Let's tell them about these things, you know,
and also talk about it to our customers while we are sourcing our flat-tip participating products in a new avatar with a insta income.
Wishing you all all the very best. Thank you.