Welcome to the future of smart investing. Are you worried of charges eating out into
your investments in a ULIP? Now look no further. Star ULIP offers exceptionally low charges,
which are the premium allocation charges as low as 7% in the first year and just 6% from
year 2 to year 4. From fifth year, there are no allocation charges, thus ensuring that
all the money gets allocated and your money grows faster. That's not all. Even the female
lives get a 0.5% extra discount. And the best part is over the period of time, the charges
get returned back to you. Allocation charge, 2x of allocation charge is returned back,
3x of the admin charge and 2x or the 3x of the mortality charges are returned back to
the policyholder over a period of time. So Star ULIP is the best choice for smart investment.
Wish you all the best for lot of selling of Star ULIP. All the best.