Hello friends, so today I am here to talk about the latest fund that we have launched.
I am talking about Sustainable Wealth 50. Why this is such a special fund, I am going
to talk about it in next 2 minutes. We see the markets are volatile, that's the basic
nature of the market. Now what are those companies, which are those companies which keep striving
even when the markets are volatile. We did our research on it and we found out the companies
which are self reliant, the companies which have very strong balance sheet, the companies
basically which are atanirbhar, what does that mean? Companies which have high cash
inflow, which have deep pockets, these are the companies which keep standing tall even
when there is a volatility in the market. We selected those 50 companies from the Nifty
500 universe and we formed this fund that we call Sustainable Wealth 50. What has been
the track record of these 50 companies? I will tell you. Last 10 years as you can see
on your screens, the returns have been as high as 25%, whereas you can see the returns
from Nifty 50 and Nifty 500 universe as well. Last 3 years, last 1 year, last 5 years, these
companies have always outperformed, not only outperformed, they have given a better and
a double CAGR than what the benchmark has been giving. Now this fund is available in
our star product in both the variants, Life Secure and 3D. Let's go all out, educate our
customers, happy selling. Thank you.