I've been thinking about what video should we shoot?
And this one's all about what to expect
your first 90 days as an agent,
because I really believe that if you're thinking
about getting in the industry,
or if you're currently in it, or you're in your 90 days,
or you're after your 90 days, and you can relate to this,
that a lot of people are getting in the industry.
They're thinking it's gonna be a cakewalk.
They're getting sold the dream.
Some MLM recruiters are like,
dude, this is freaking phenomenal.
You're gonna make so much money.
Oh my gosh, it's insane.
I'm here to tell you, it is difficult.
It is not easy.
Now, it can be easy, okay?
But if I just say, dude, this industry is easy, like I'm lying because 92% of insurance agents fell.
Even when I got out and made $117,000, my first full month, $117,000 my first eight months, it still wasn't easy because I had to work my butt off.
So I'm going to kind of go through like the psychology of how you can succeed your first 90 days.
Also, too, though, I want you thinking about like as an example.
a lot of people get in the industry and they become really overwhelmed by all of the
companies available right all the carriers all the different products all different commission
levels all the different ways to get in front of people all different terminology right and
different product specifics and the ins and outs of like all the writers and benefits and all the
stuff that like maybe you didn't maybe wasn't on your test and it's funny when you take your
insurance test, you end up using very little full transparency, shoot the messenger, freaking
obliterate me in comments. If I'm wrong, you end up using very little of what you studied for,
what you memorized and what you took a test on. You know what I mean? Like they're not like,
you know, all this money laundering stuff. Yeah, it's good. Freaking don't, you know,
launder money, dude. People know that like that's, that's a common sense, right? But you don't end
up encountering that a lot as an agent, you know? And if you're out there like, dude, I
I encounter that all the time.
People are constantly wanting to launder money with me and put it in life policies and then take it out and scam people and I like this is not true Okay So a lot of this stuff that you studying for you don end up using but here one thing I can tell you this the people that succeed the best in the first 90 days
the first 180 days, the first 365 days, first two and three years, they become less worried
about all of the intricate details. Because what happens is you get analysis paralysis.
you want to know everything before you do anything. And I can tell you what,
if that, if you're being honest with yourself and you have that personality style,
and a lot of people do, I'm not saying you can't succeed in insurance, but I am saying it's going
to be more difficult because you're going to want to know stuff before you do stuff.
And the answer for succeeding in insurance is just getting in front of people. It's just activity.
it's just doing more and I'm just keeping it real when I say that right so we talk through being
overwhelmed that's common happens to a lot of people we get really like foggy and we want we
like it we get paralyzed because we don't know what to do we're like well crap I want to make
calls Cody I want to make calls man but what if they say how much does it cost what if they say
how long have you been selling insurance what if they say i'm not interested it's like really
what's funny is we think you think a lot of people think maybe not you i don't know think
that you need to know the specifics you've got to understand all the intricate details
and that you need this like perfect phrasing and this super secret ninja phrase like a lot more of
this is to this business is is a lot more than just sales training by the way right like yeah
That's important.
My book, Zero to Six Figures,
talks a lot about sales training you can get at Amazon.
But it a lot more than just sales training Like as an example finding the right company to work with is super important because I believe in niching down I believe in learning a product I believe in mastering
and becoming an expert at something at some point, but also believe in doing a lot and getting in
front of people. And so if you're ever like, man, I don't know if I'm at the right home.
I'm thinking about leaving the industry. I want a new agency to work with. I want to meet some
other people in the space that Cody, that you trust, because I get a lot of questions, man,
who should I work with? Whatever. We have a new program available. You can go to agentplacementprogram.com.
The link's in the description below already by default. And you can click on that and go and
read more, watch the video, put your information in, and then we can refer you to an agency to
work with, right? Like I'm not personally recruiting for me, but I am trying to play
matchmaker and help agents and agencies and keep you from leaving because I don't want you to leave.
Okay. Right. But the people that, that want to analyze everything are going to have a little
tougher because you just need to know that you feel like you need to know stuff. Right. But the
people that are just, that just go at this thing and focus on getting in front of people and winning
and doing the activity. And if a mentor or a coach tells you to do something, now, if they tell you
something that tell you to do something, but I'm telling you to do the opposite, dude,
that's a tough, that's a tough scenario because if they believe something, but I believe something,
you know what I mean? That's tough. If you're working with them every day in their office,
dude, try whatever they're saying. If it doesn't work, do it my way. Probably work, right? But
you've got to take action no matter what. Okay. Second thing is the niche. Yes, you can be
overwhelmed, but then you got to pick a niche, man. Like you've got to get really good at owning
a lane. I sold life insurance my first year and I did it by cold calling and cold door knocking
people that were between the ages of 50 and 85 I just did about burial and final expenses and all that kind of stuff Right And it was through it was it was cold calling cold door knocking It was um I used to have call nights
at the office and I bring people in. We also used to do, um, uh, work the warm market. I didn't work
a lot of leads, you know, my first couple of years, full transparency. I did not. I saw the
benefits of doing that at some point and just hadn't yet. Right. But the second is, is the
niche. You need to own a niche because you can get good at, you can learn a lot in a niche.
You can say the same things over and over again. You can get in a cycle and a consistency and a
rhythm so that you can start making money every week. I was talking to someone earlier and they're
like, man, I've made like five grand so far these first several months. I'm like,
you should be thinking, dude, how do I do what I did, but do it in a week,
every week, how to make five grand, which leads me to the next piece, which is prospecting.
this is the part that is overlooked the most because you think i need product knowledge
you think i gotta know everything about the carriers you think dude i got no sales and
closing and if they say you know this stuff it's like dude none of these other things matter
if you cannot get in front of someone i believe in getting in front of at least 10 people and
you can do that part-time by the way i got in front of 10 people a week part-time
you got to get in front of 10 people every single week to succeed in this business and if you're not
asking 10 people minimum to do business with you, you will 1000% fail. And so I want to get these
90 days started off right. This is what you can expect. Your first 90 days as an agent,
you can succeed. You can have a ton of fun. Most don't. Most do not do well. Most do not make a
bunch of money, but that doesn't mean you can't. Welcome back to the CA Power Players Podcast.
We've had the Mr. David Dufour back in Springfield Mo in the studio.
Dave, welcome back.
Greetings and salutations.
Dude.
I love spending time with you, man.
Well, thank you.
I do too.
I really do.
It's fun.
You're such a great host.
We've had such a nice time at Chipotle a couple times.
Yeah, man.